<root>
    <category name="Untrusted Input Handling or Injection Flaws">
        <rule>
            <name>Untrusted Data in 'document.getElementById().value'</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[document\.getElementById\(.+\)\.value]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:document\.getElementById\(.+\)\.value][IF(PRESENT:(innerHTML|outerHTML|document\.write|eval\(|setTimeout\(|setInterval\(|fetch\(|XMLHttpRequest|location\.) && MISSING:(DOMPurify|sanitize|encodeURI|encodeURIComponent|textContent|innerText))]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>3</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects the usage of unvalidated input.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>This rule matches instances where user input obtained from `document.getElementById().value` is used without proper validation. Unvalidated input can lead to security vulnerabilities such as injection attacks, cross-site scripting (XSS), and improper data handling.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Validate and sanitize user input obtained through `document. getElementById(). value` before using it in any sensitive operations. Implement input validation techniques appropriate for the expected input, such as data type checking, length validation, and character filtering.</developer>
            <reviewer>Ensure that proper input handling is in place for user input obtained through `document. getElementById(). value`. Verify that developers have implemented appropriate input validation and sanitization techniques to prevent security vulnerabilities related to unvalidated input. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Untrusted Data in InnerHTML</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[\.innerHTML\s?=\s?.+]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:\.innerHTML\s?=\s?.+][IF(MISSING:DOMPurify\.sanitize|sanitizeHtml|textContent|innerText|escapeHtml|encodeHTML && MISSING:test|example|spec)]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>3</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects potential security risks when assigning untrusted data to the innerHTML property.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>This rule matches instances where potentially untrusted data is assigned to the innerHTML property. Assigning untrusted data directly to innerHTML can lead to cross-site scripting (XSS) vulnerabilities if proper input validation and output encoding are not performed.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Avoid assigning untrusted data directly to the innerHTML property. Implement proper input validation and output encoding techniques when updating the content of elements via innerHTML to prevent XSS vulnerabilities.</developer>
            <reviewer>Potentially untrusted data is assigned to the innerHTML property. Assess whether the code implements proper input validation and output encoding techniques to prevent XSS vulnerabilities when updating element content. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Untrusted Data in 'document.write'</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[document\.write\(|innerHTML\s?=\s?.+]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:document\.write\(|innerHTML\s?=\s?.+][IF(MISSING:DOMPurify\.sanitize|sanitizeHtml|textContent|innerText|escapeHtml|encodeHTML && MISSING:test|example|spec)]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>3</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects potential DOM-based cross-site scripting (XSS) vulnerabilities.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>This rule matches instances where the `document.write()` function or the assignment of potentially untrusted values to the `innerHTML` property is performed. These actions can introduce DOM-based cross-site scripting vulnerabilities if proper input validation and output encoding are not applied.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Avoid using `document. write()` and should implement appropriate input validation and output encoding techniques when assigning values to the `innerHTML` property. Ensure that user-supplied data is properly sanitized and encoded to prevent XSS attacks.</developer>
            <reviewer>The code uses `document. write()` or assigns potentially untrusted values to the `innerHTML` property. Assess whether proper input validation and output encoding techniques are implemented to prevent DOM-based cross-site scripting vulnerabilities. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Untrusted Input in Web/API Response">
        <rule>
            <name>Handlebars Unescaped String</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[\{\{\{.*?\}\}\}]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:\{\{\{.*?\}\}\}][IF(MISSING:(sanitize|escape|xss|safeHtml))]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>3</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <description>Detects unescaped Handlebars strings in code.</description>
            <rule_desc>Detects instances of unescaped Handlebars strings in the code, which can indicate a potential security vulnerability.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates the potential vulnerability of unescaped Handlebars strings in the code. Unescaped strings can lead to cross-site scripting (XSS) vulnerabilities if user input is not properly escaped or sanitized before rendering.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>User input used with Handlebars strings is properly sanitized or escaped to prevent XSS attacks. Handlebars provides built-in mechanisms for escaping user input, but triple curly braces can bypass this. Developers should follow secure coding practices and sanitize or escape user-generated content before using it in Handlebars strings.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify that proper input sanitization techniques are applied when using Handlebars strings. Ensure that developers use Handlebars' built-in escaping mechanisms or equivalent custom sanitization methods to mitigate the risk of XSS vulnerabilities. Also assess the implementation of output encoding and confirm that user input is properly sanitized before rendering it in the application. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Insecure Method/Function Call">
        <rule>
            <name>Insecure Method Call: child_process.exec()</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(^|\s|=\s?)require\(\s*('|")child_process('|")\s*\)(\s*\.(\s*\w+\s*)*\()?\s*\)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(^|\s|=\s?)require\(\s*('|")child_process('|")\s*\)(\s*\.(\s*\w+\s*)*\()?\s*\)]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>3</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects the usage of the `require('child_process')` statement with the `exec()` function, which can introduce remote OS command execution vulnerabilities.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates the potential vulnerability of using the `child_process.exec()` function to execute operating system commands. Attackers can manipulate user input or crafted data to execute arbitrary commands on the host system, leading to unauthorized access, data breaches, or system compromise.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Exercise caution when using the `child_process. exec()` function and ensure that any user input passed to it is properly validated, sanitized, and restricted to prevent command injection vulnerabilities. It is recommended to use safer alternatives, such as using predefined functions or libraries specifically designed for safe command execution or employing proper input validation and sanitization techniques.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify whether the code implements sufficient measures to prevent remote OS command execution vulnerabilities. Check whether the usage of `child_process. exec()` is necessary, and if so, ensure that proper input validation, sanitization, and command parameterization techniques are implemented to prevent command injection attacks. Also assess the context in which this function is used and verify that security best practices are followed to mitigate any potential risks. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Insecure Method Call: eval|setTimeout|setInterval</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[\b(eval|setTimeout|setInterval)\(.+\)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:\b(eval|setTimeout|setInterval)\(.+\)][IF(PRESENT:(\+|`|\$\{|location|document\.cookie|localStorage|sessionStorage|req\.|res\.) && MISSING:allowlist|whitelist|JSON\.parse|Function\s*\(|trusted|DOMPurify && MISSING:function\s*\(|=>\s*\{|callback|test|example|spec|mock)]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>3</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects the usage of the `eval`, `setTimeout`, and `setInterval` functions.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>This rule matches instances where the `eval`, `setTimeout`, or `setInterval` functions are used. These functions can introduce security vulnerabilities if not used carefully, as they can execute arbitrary code and lead to code injection or unintended consequences.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Avoid using the `eval`, `setTimeout`, and `setInterval` functions whenever possible. If their usage is necessary, developers should carefully validate and sanitize any input used within these functions to prevent code injection vulnerabilities.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify whether the code uses the `eval`, `setTimeout`, or `setInterval` functions. Assess whether the usage is justified and if proper input validation and sanitization techniques are implemented to prevent code injection vulnerabilities. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Cryptographic Issues">
        <rule>
            <name>Weak Cryptography</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(CryptoJS\.DES\.encrypt|MD5|SHA-1|RC4)\(.+\)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(CryptoJS\.DES\.encrypt|MD5|SHA-1|RC4)\(.+\)]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects the usage of weak cryptographic functions.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>This rule matches instances where weak cryptographic functions, such as `CryptoJS.DES.encrypt`, `MD5`, `SHA-1`, or `RC4`, are used. These algorithms are cryptographically broken or weak and should not be used for security-sensitive operations.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use stronger and more secure cryptographic functions and algorithms, such as AES-256 or SHA-256, for encryption and hashing operations. Also follow best practices for key management and encryption protocols.</developer>
            <reviewer>Weak cryptographic functions are used in the code. Assess whether the code uses secure cryptographic algorithms and if best practices for encryption and hashing are followed. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Weak Random Number Generation</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[Math\.random\(.*\)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:Math\.random\(.*\)][IF(PRESENT:(token|secret|nonce|otp|session|password|key))]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects the usage of Math.random() in security-sensitive contexts.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Math.random() is not cryptographically secure and produces predictable values. Using it to generate tokens, session identifiers, nonces, or cryptographic keys can lead to predictable output that attackers can guess or reproduce.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use `crypto.getRandomValues()` or the `crypto.randomUUID()` / `crypto.randomBytes()` APIs for any security-critical random number generation. Math.random() is acceptable only for non-security uses such as UI animations or sampling.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify that Math.random() is not used where cryptographic randomness is required. Confirm that security-sensitive identifiers use a CSPRNG. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Information Disclosure">
        <rule>
            <name>Routes</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(?i)route:\s+'.*(\s?)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(?i)route:\s+'.*(\s?)]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects the presence of hardcoded routes in JavaScript code, which may expose sensitive information or introduce security risks.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates the presence of hardcoded routes in the JavaScript code. Hardcoded routes may expose sensitive information, such as internal URLs, API endpoints, or authentication routes, to potential attackers. Hardcoded routes can also lead to security vulnerabilities, such as insufficient access control, information disclosure, or bypassing security mechanisms.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Avoid hardcoding routes in JavaScript code and instead consider using configuration files or dynamic route handling mechanisms. Hardcoding routes can introduce security risks and make the codebase less maintainable. By implementing dynamic routing solutions, developers can improve flexibility, allow for easier configuration changes, and minimize the exposure of sensitive information.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify whether the code contains hardcoded routes and assess the potential security implications. Ensure that sensitive information, such as internal URLs, API endpoints, or authentication routes, is not exposed through hardcoded routes. Also check if the code implements appropriate access control measures and adheres to secure coding practices, such as using configuration files or dynamic routing mechanisms. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Stack Trace or Error Disclosure (Node/Express)</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[res\.(?:send|json|end)\s*\(\s*err(?:or)?(?:\.stack|\.message)?\s*\)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:res\.(?:send|json|end)\s*\(\s*err(?:or)?(?:\.stack|\.message)?\s*\)][IF(MISSING:statusCode|status\s*\(\s*[45]|genericMessage|sanitize|message\s*:\s*["'])]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects Node/Express response patterns that send raw error objects or stack traces directly to HTTP clients.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Sending raw error objects or stack traces in HTTP responses discloses internal file paths, library versions, and execution context to attackers, aiding reconnaissance and exploitation.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Return a generic error message to the client and log the detailed error server-side only. Use an error handler middleware that maps exceptions to safe, sanitized HTTP responses.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm that HTTP responses never include raw error objects, stack traces, or internal diagnostic details. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Node Runtime Hardening">
        <rule>
            <name>Node Inspector Exposed via --inspect</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[\B--inspect(?:-brk)?(?:=\S+)?\b]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:\B--inspect(?:-brk)?(?:=\S+)?\b]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>1</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>1</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>file</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects Node.js debug inspector flags that may expose a remotely reachable debug endpoint.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If debug inspector is exposed beyond localhost, attackers may gain high-impact introspection or code execution capabilities.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Disable inspector in production, or bind strictly to localhost behind controlled access and network restrictions.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify runtime scripts and deployment manifests do not expose inspector endpoints in production environments. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Insecure HTTP Parser Enabled</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[\binsecureHTTPParser\s*:\s*true\b]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:\binsecureHTTPParser\s*:\s*true\b]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>1</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>1</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>file</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects explicit enablement of Node's insecure HTTP parser option.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Using insecure parsing behavior can increase request-smuggling and parser ambiguity risks in proxy/backend chains.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Avoid enabling insecure parser options and align HTTP parsing behavior with hardened defaults.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm parser hardening remains enabled across app servers and reverse-proxy boundaries. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Insecure/Weak Mitigations">
        <rule>
            <name>Weak Mitigation: Using disable|bypass|ignore|suppress|unsafe</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[\b(disable|bypass|ignore|suppress|unsafe)\b]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:\b(disable|bypass|ignore|suppress|unsafe)\b][IF(PRESENT:(auth|csrf|xss|cors|tls|ssl|verify|validation|sanitize|security) && MISSING:(example|sample|dummy|test|placeholder))]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects weak or inadequate security mitigations.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>This rule matches instances where weak or inadequate security mitigations (such as disable, bypass, ignore, suppress, or unsafe) are used. Weak mitigations can lead to security vulnerabilities or provide a false sense of security, leaving the application exposed to attacks.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Avoid using weak or inadequate security mitigations as they can create vulnerabilities in the application. Implement strong and effective security measures that follow established best practices and standards.</developer>
            <reviewer>Identify weak or inadequate security mitigations in the code and recommend implementing stronger security measures. Assess whether the application applies appropriate security controls and avoids relying on weak mitigations that may be easily bypassed by attackers. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Database Queries">
        <rule>
            <name>SQL Query: SELECT Statements with WHERE or ORDER BY</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(?i)\bSELECT\s+?\*?\s+?FROM\s+[^\s]+\s+(WHERE|ORDER BY)\b.*]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(?i)\bSELECT\s+?\*?\s+?FROM\s+[^\s]+\s+(WHERE|ORDER BY)\b.*][IF(PRESENT:(\+|`|\$\{|req\.|params|query|body) && MISSING:(\?|prepare|bind|replacements|sequelize\.query\s*\(.*replacements))]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>3</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects SELECT statements with WHERE or ORDER BY clauses in SQL queries, which may be vulnerable to SQL injection if user input is not handled securely in JavaScript environments.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates the use of potentially vulnerable SELECT statements with WHERE or ORDER BY clauses. Improper handling of user input in these clauses can lead to SQL injection, allowing attackers to manipulate query behavior and gain unauthorized access to data.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Validate and implement secure alternatives, such as using parameterized queries or query bindings provided by JavaScript libraries like `mysql`, `pg`, or ORMs such as Sequelize to avoid SQL injection risks.</developer>
            <reviewer>Check if parameterized queries or query bindings are used with SELECT statements containing WHERE or ORDER BY clauses in JavaScript applications to ensure secure handling of user input. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>SQL Query: Unrestricted SELECT *</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[\bSELECT\s+\*\s+FROM\b]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:\bSELECT\s+\*\s+FROM\b]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects "SELECT * FROM" in SQL queries, which can expose unnecessary or sensitive data in JavaScript applications.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it suggests that the query retrieves more data than necessary, potentially exposing sensitive information and increasing the attack surface.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Validate and specify only necessary columns in SQL queries rather than using "SELECT *" to prevent unnecessary data exposure. This is especially important when working with libraries like `mysql` or `pg` in Node. js.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify that SQL queries in JavaScript applications select only the required columns to minimize data exposure risks. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>SQL Query: Non-parameterized INSERT Statements</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(?i)\bINSERT\s+INTO\s+[^\s]+\s+\(.*=.*\$.*\)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(?i)\bINSERT\s+INTO\s+[^\s]+\s+\(.*=.*\$.*\)][IF(MISSING:\?|prepare|bind|replacements|sequelize\.query\s*\(.*replacements|mysql\.escape|pg\.escape)]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>3</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects non-parameterized INSERT statements that may include user input directly, leading to SQL injection vulnerabilities in JavaScript environments.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates a potentially vulnerable INSERT statement that could allow SQL injection if user input is included without proper handling.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use parameterized queries or prepared statements in INSERT operations to prevent SQL injection attacks when using JavaScript libraries like `mysql`, `pg`, or ORMs such as Sequelize.</developer>
            <reviewer>Inspect any INSERT statements to confirm secure parameterization in JavaScript applications and ensure that user input is handled safely to minimize injection risks. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Deprecated SQL Functions</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(?i)\b(mysql_query|pg_query|sqlite_query|db.query|db.execute|knex.raw)\s*\(\s*['\"]?SELECT|INSERT|UPDATE|DELETE\s+.+\s*['\"]?\s*\.\s*\$([a-zA-Z_\x7f-\xff][a-zA-Z0-9_\x7f-\xff]*)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(?i)\b(mysql_query|pg_query|sqlite_query|db.query|db.execute|knex.raw)\s*\(][IF(PRESENT:(\+|`|\$\{|req\.|params|query|body) && MISSING:(\?|prepare|bind|replacements))]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>3</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects usage of deprecated or insecure SQL functions and dynamic SQL queries that may lead to security vulnerabilities in JavaScript applications.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates the usage of potentially insecure SQL functions or libraries that may be vulnerable to SQL injection or other security issues if used without proper configurations or parameterization.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Avoid using deprecated SQL functions or dynamic query building, and instead use secure alternatives like prepared statements or parameterized queries available in Node. js libraries (`mysql`, `pg`, Sequelize).</developer>
            <reviewer>Check for deprecated SQL functions or dynamic SQL building with user input, ensuring secure alternatives are implemented and that input validation and query parameterization practices are followed in JavaScript applications. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Deprecated Functions">
        <rule>
            <name>Deprecated JS Function: escape|unescape|eval</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[\b(escape|unescape|eval)\b]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:\b(escape|unescape|eval)\b][IF(MISSING:JSON\.parse|Function\s*\(|trusted|allowlist|DOMPurify && MISSING:test|example|spec|mock)]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects usage of deprecated JavaScript functions.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>This rule matches instances where deprecated JavaScript functions (such as escape, unescape, or eval) are used. Deprecated functions may have security vulnerabilities or compatibility issues and should be replaced with modern, safer alternatives.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Avoid using deprecated JavaScript functions as they may introduce security vulnerabilities. update their code to use modern alternatives and follow best practices to ensure the security and compatibility of their applications.</developer>
            <reviewer>Check for the usage of deprecated JavaScript functions and recommend replacing them with safer alternatives. Assess whether the codebase follows best practices and avoids deprecated functions that may pose security risks. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="MISC Checks">
        <rule>
            <name>Insecure Direct Object References (IDOR)</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(req\.params|req\.query|req\.body)[\s\S]*?(\[|\.)[\s\S]*?]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(req\.params|req\.query|req\.body)[\s\S]*?(\[|\.)[\s\S]*?][IF(PRESENT:(findByPk|findOne|findAll|where|delete|update|patch|put|remove|destroy) && MISSING:(authorize|isAuthorized|canAccess|hasRole|ownership|tenantId))]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>3</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects potential Insecure Direct Object References (IDOR).</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>This rule matches potential Insecure Direct Object References (IDOR) vulnerabilities in the code. IDOR occurs when user-supplied input is used directly to access internal resources or sensitive objects without proper authorization or validation. Attackers can manipulate the input to access unauthorized resources, view sensitive data, or perform actions they are not allowed to.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Implement proper authorization and access control mechanisms to prevent IDOR vulnerabilities. User input used to access resources should be validated, sanitized, and authorized based on the user's privileges. Additionally, developers should use indirect references or randomized identifiers to obfuscate direct object references.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify whether the code implements proper authorization and access control mechanisms to prevent IDOR vulnerabilities. Check whether user input used to access resources is properly validated, sanitized, and authorized. Reviewers should assess the effectiveness of the implemented measures in mitigating IDOR risks. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Server-Side Request Forgery (SSRF)</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[XMLHttpRequest\.open\(|fetch\(|axios\.get\(|http\.request\(|https\.request\(|http\.get\(|https\.get\(|http\.post\(|https\.post\(|http\.put\(|https\.put\(|http\.delete\(|https\.delete\(|\$.ajax\({\s*url:\s*['"].+['"]]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:XMLHttpRequest\.open\(|fetch\(|axios\.get\(|http\.request\(|https\.request\(|http\.get\(|https\.get\(|http\.post\(|https\.post\(|http\.put\(|https\.put\(|http\.delete\(|https\.delete\(|\$.ajax\({\s*url:\s*['"].+['"]][IF(PRESENT:(req\.|params|query|body|userInput|target|url) && MISSING:(allowlist|whitelist|isPrivateIPBlocked|validateUrl|new URL\())]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>3</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects potential server-side request forgery (SSRF) vulnerabilities.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>This rule matches instances where XMLHttpRequest, fetch, axios, http.request, https.request, http.get, https.get, http.post, https.post, http.put, https.put, http.delete, https.delete, or $.ajax functions are used with potentially untrusted URLs. Improper usage of these functions can lead to SSRF vulnerabilities, allowing attackers to make unauthorized requests to internal resources.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Implement proper input validation and sanitization when using XMLHttpRequest, fetch, axios, http. request, https. request, http. get, https. get, http. post, https. post, http. put, https. put, http. delete, https. delete, or $. ajax functions. Validate and restrict the URLs to trusted sources to prevent SSRF attacks.</developer>
            <reviewer>XMLHttpRequest, fetch, axios, http. request, https. request, http. get, https. get, http. post, https. post, http. put, https. put, http. delete, https. delete, or $. ajax functions are used with potentially untrusted URLs. Assess whether proper input validation and URL restriction mechanisms are implemented to mitigate SSRF vulnerabilities. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Prototype Pollution</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(\b__proto__\b|Object\.prototype\.(?!hasOwnProperty)[a-zA-Z]+\s?=)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(\b__proto__\b|Object\.prototype\.(?!hasOwnProperty)[a-zA-Z]+\s?=)][IF(MISSING:Object\.freeze|hasOwnProperty|Object\.create\s*\(\s*null|__proto__.*check)]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>3</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects potential prototype pollution vulnerabilities.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>This rule matches instances where the `__proto__` property or assignment to properties of `Object.prototype` (excluding `hasOwnProperty`) is performed. These actions can lead to prototype pollution vulnerabilities, allowing attackers to modify the behavior of objects and potentially compromise the application's security.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Avoid using or modifying the `__proto__` property directly, and exercise caution when extending or modifying properties of `Object. prototype`. Use safer alternatives, such as `Object. create()` or creating new objects with specific prototypes.</developer>
            <reviewer>The code directly uses or modifies the `__proto__` property or assigns values to properties of `Object. prototype` (excluding `hasOwnProperty`). Assess whether proper precautions are taken to prevent prototype pollution vulnerabilities. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Missing Cookie Security Flags</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[res\.cookie\s*\(|document\.cookie\s*=]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:res\.cookie\s*\(|document\.cookie\s*=][IF(MISSING:httpOnly\s*:\s*true|secure\s*:\s*true|sameSite|SameSite)]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>1</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>1</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>file</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects cookie creation without essential security flags such as httpOnly, secure, and SameSite.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Cookies set without httpOnly are accessible to JavaScript and vulnerable to XSS-based theft. Cookies without the secure flag are transmitted over HTTP. Cookies without SameSite are vulnerable to cross-site request forgery (CSRF).</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Always set httpOnly:true, secure:true, and sameSite:'Strict' or 'Lax' on session and authentication cookies. Example: res.cookie('session', value, { httpOnly: true, secure: true, sameSite: 'Strict' }).</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm that all cookies setting session or authentication state include httpOnly, secure, and sameSite attributes. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
</root>
