<root>
    <category name="Injection">
        <rule>
            <name>Invoke-Expression with Variable Input</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[Invoke-Expression\s+["']?.*\$\w|iex\s+["']?.*\$\w]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:Invoke-Expression\s+["']?.*\$\w|iex\s+["']?.*\$\w][IF(MISSING:Validate|Sanitize|allowlist|\[ValidateSet\]|\[ValidatePattern\])]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>3</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects Invoke-Expression (iex) calls that include variable interpolation.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Invoke-Expression with unsanitized variables enables arbitrary PowerShell code execution, which can be exploited for privilege escalation or lateral movement.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Avoid Invoke-Expression entirely. Use structured calls, cmdlets, and parameter validation attributes ([ValidateSet], [ValidatePattern]) instead.</developer>
            <reviewer>Trace the origin of the string passed to Invoke-Expression and confirm no attacker-controlled path reaches it. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Start-Process or cmd.exe with Variable Arguments</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(?:Start-Process|&\s+cmd(?:\.exe)?|Invoke-Command)\s+[^`\n]*\$(?:args|input|params|\w+URL|\w+Path|\w+Cmd)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(?:Start-Process|&\s+cmd(?:\.exe)?|Invoke-Command)\s+[^`\n]*\$(?:args|input|params|\w+URL|\w+Path|\w+Cmd)][IF(MISSING:EscapeShellArgument|Sanitize|\[ValidatePattern\])]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>3</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects process invocation with variable arguments that may contain unsanitized input.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Injecting attacker-controlled arguments into process invocations can lead to argument injection, command execution, or path traversal.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Validate and escape all arguments using structured parameter passing. Avoid building command strings through concatenation.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify argument sources and confirm no user-supplied data reaches process invocations unescaped. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Sensitive Data Exposure">
        <rule>
            <name>Hardcoded Credential in PowerShell Script</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(?i)(?:password|passwd|secret|apikey|api_key|token|accesskey)\s*=\s*["'][A-Za-z0-9@#$%^&*!_\-]{8,}["']]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(?i)(?:password|passwd|secret|apikey|api_key|token|accesskey)\s*=\s*["'][A-Za-z0-9@#$%^&*!_\-]{8,}["']][IF(MISSING:SecureString|Get-Secret|Vault|\$env:)]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>1</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>0</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>file</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects hardcoded credentials or secrets assigned as plaintext string variables.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Plaintext secrets in PowerShell scripts are exposed through source control, script block logging, and transcript files.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use SecureString, Windows Credential Manager, PSCredential, or secrets management tools (e.g., Get-Secret from SecretManagement module). Never store secrets as plaintext strings.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm no credential assignments use plaintext string literals. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>ConvertTo-SecureString with PlainText</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[ConvertTo-SecureString\s+.*-AsPlainText\s+-Force|ConvertTo-SecureString\s+.*-Force\s+.*-AsPlainText]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:ConvertTo-SecureString\s+.*-AsPlainText\s+-Force]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>1</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>0</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>file</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects ConvertTo-SecureString usage with -AsPlainText -Force flags indicating a plaintext credential workflow.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Using -AsPlainText with a hardcoded or logged string defeats the purpose of SecureString, as the plaintext is visible in script block logs and memory.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Retrieve credentials from secure storage (SecretManagement, Credential Manager) rather than converting plaintext strings.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify that the source string is not hardcoded or logged. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Download and Execution">
        <rule>
            <name>Download Cradle Pattern</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(?:IEX|Invoke-Expression)\s*\(\s*(?:New-Object\s+Net\.WebClient|Invoke-WebRequest|iwr|curl|wget)\s*[^)]*\)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(?:IEX|Invoke-Expression)\s*\(\s*(?:New-Object\s+Net\.WebClient|Invoke-WebRequest|iwr|curl|wget)\s*[^)]*\)]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects download-and-execute cradle patterns commonly used in living-off-the-land attacks.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Download cradles fetch and immediately execute remote code, bypassing code signing controls and enabling supply chain attacks or post-exploitation persistence.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use signed scripts from trusted repositories. Validate content hashes before execution. Enforce code signing policies.</developer>
            <reviewer>This pattern is a high-confidence indicator of malicious activity in most production environments. Verify the remote source and confirm a legitimate use case exists. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>WebClient DownloadString Execution</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(?:New-Object\s+(?:System\.)?Net\.WebClient|Net\.WebClient\b)[^|;\n]*\.\s*DownloadString]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(?:New-Object\s+(?:System\.)?Net\.WebClient|Net\.WebClient\b)[^|;\n]*\.\s*DownloadString][IF(MISSING:checksum|hash|signature|verify)]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects WebClient.DownloadString without content verification, often used to fetch and execute remote scripts.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Downloading and executing remote scripts without signature or hash verification exposes systems to tampered or malicious code substitution.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use Invoke-WebRequest with hash validation. Enforce AllSigned or RemoteSigned execution policies and verify content authenticity before execution.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm the download source is trusted and content integrity is validated before use. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Execution Policy and Security Controls">
        <rule>
            <name>Bypass Execution Policy</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(?i)-ExecutionPolicy\s+(?:Bypass|Unrestricted)|Set-ExecutionPolicy\s+(?:Bypass|Unrestricted)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(?i)-ExecutionPolicy\s+(?:Bypass|Unrestricted)|Set-ExecutionPolicy\s+(?:Bypass|Unrestricted)]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects PowerShell execution policy bypass or unrestricted policy settings.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Bypassing or disabling execution policy removes a defense-in-depth control that prevents unsigned scripts from running, enabling attackers to execute arbitrary PowerShell.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use AllSigned or RemoteSigned policies in production. If bypass is required for automation, use a scoped policy with signed scripts.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify whether the bypass is used in authorized automation or represents a security control bypass. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>AMSI Bypass Attempt</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[amsiInitFailed|AmsiScanBuffer|amsi\.dll|amsiContext|Disable.*AMSI|AMSI.*bypass]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:amsiInitFailed|AmsiScanBuffer|amsi\.dll|amsiContext|Disable.*AMSI|AMSI.*bypass]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>3</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects known patterns associated with Antimalware Scan Interface (AMSI) bypass techniques.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>AMSI bypass patterns are used to evade PowerShell-based malware detection, allowing execution of malicious payloads without antivirus scanning.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>These patterns have no legitimate use in production code. Remove any code that modifies AMSI behavior.</developer>
            <reviewer>Any occurrence of these patterns in production code should be treated as a high-severity indicator of compromise or intentional security bypass. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Network and Transport">
        <rule>
            <name>TLS Validation Disabled via Callback</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[ServerCertificateValidationCallback\s*=\s*\{[^}]*\$true\}|ServerCertificateValidationCallback\s*=\s*\{\s*\$true\s*\}|IgnoreSSL|DisableCertCheck|CertificatePolicy.*Accept]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:ServerCertificateValidationCallback\s*=\s*\{[^}]*\$true\}|ServerCertificateValidationCallback\s*=\s*\{\s*\$true\s*\}]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects TLS certificate validation disabled via ServerCertificateValidationCallback returning true for all certificates.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Disabling certificate validation makes HTTPS connections vulnerable to MITM attacks by accepting any certificate including forged or expired ones.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Remove certificate validation overrides. Use proper certificate management and trusted CA bundles.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm no production code accepts all TLS certificates unconditionally. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
</root>
