<root>
    <category name="AndroidManifest.xml - Insecure Misconfiguration">
        <rule>
            <name>Insecure Permissions</name>
            <regex>android\.permission\.(WRITE_EXTERNAL_STORAGE|READ_EXTERNAL_STORAGE|ACCESS_FINE_LOCATION|ACCESS_COARSE_LOCATION)</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/insecure_permissions.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>0</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>file</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects insecure permissions that can pose security risks.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Granting unnecessary permissions or overly broad permissions, such as WRITE_EXTERNAL_STORAGE, READ_EXTERNAL_STORAGE, INTERNET, ACCESS_FINE_LOCATION, or ACCESS_COARSE_LOCATION, can lead to security vulnerabilities. Malicious apps or attackers can exploit these permissions to access sensitive user data, track user location, or perform unauthorized actions.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Carefully review and minimize the permissions requested by the application. Only request permissions that are necessary for the app's functionality and follow the principle of least privilege.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify that the AndroidManifest.xml file requests only the permissions necessary for the application's functionality. Ensure that unnecessary or overly broad permissions are not granted, as they can pose security risks. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Content Providers with No Permissions</name>
            <regex>&lt;provider\b|android:authorities\s*=</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/content_providers_with_no_permissions.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>0</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>file</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects content providers without specific permissions.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Content providers without specific permissions may expose sensitive data to unauthorized applications or components. Without proper permission checks, other applications can potentially access or modify the data managed by the content provider, leading to security vulnerabilities.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Specify appropriate permissions for content providers to restrict access to authorized applications or components. Review the android:permission attribute and ensure that sensitive data is protected from unauthorized access.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify that content providers have appropriate permissions set to restrict access to authorized applications or components. Ensure that sensitive data managed by content providers is protected from unauthorized access. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Exported Components</name>
            <regex>android:exported\s*=\s*"(true|TRUE)"</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/exported_components.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>3</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>1</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects exported components that can pose security risks.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Exported components, such as activities, services, or broadcast receivers, that are marked as exported="true" can be accessed by other applications or components. This can lead to security vulnerabilities if sensitive functionality or data is exposed to unauthorized entities.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Review the exported components in the AndroidManifest.xml file and ensure that only necessary components are exported. Components that do not need to be accessed by other applications should not be exported.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify that only necessary components are marked as exported in the AndroidManifest.xml file. Ensure that sensitive functionality or data is not exposed to unauthorized entities through exported components. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Allow Backup</name>
            <regex>android:allowBackup\s*=\s*"(true|TRUE)"</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/allow_backup.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>1</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>0</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>file</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects the use of allowBackup="true" in the application's manifest.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>The allowBackup attribute, when set to "true", allows the application's data to be backed up to external storage. This can lead to security risks if sensitive data is stored insecurely or if the backup is accessible to unauthorized entities.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Carefully consider whether allowing backup of application data is necessary. If sensitive data is stored, it should be encrypted or excluded from backup using the android:allowBackup attribute set to "false".</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify that sensitive data is not being backed up insecurely by checking the value of the allowBackup attribute in the AndroidManifest.xml file. Ensure that sensitive data is properly protected and not exposed to unauthorized access through backup mechanisms. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Unprotected Components: Empty Permission Attribute</name>
            <regex>android:permission\s*=\s*(?:""|'')</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/unprotected_components_empty_permission_attribute.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>0</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>file</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects components with an explicitly empty android:permission attribute, which removes all access control.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Setting android:permission="" explicitly grants any application access to the component, equivalent to having no protection at all. This is more dangerous than omitting the attribute because it overrides any parent-level permission and signals an intentional but misconfigured access policy.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Remove the empty permission attribute and replace it with a meaningful custom permission (e.g. com.example.permission.MY_FEATURE) or use android:exported="false" to restrict access to the current app only.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm that no component has android:permission set to an empty string. Verify that sensitive components are protected by appropriate permissions or restricted via exported="false". This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Debuggable Application</name>
            <regex>android:debuggable\s*=\s*"(true|TRUE)"</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/debuggable_application.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>1</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>0</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>file</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects debuggable applications.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Setting android:debuggable="true" in the application's manifest allows debugging of the application, potentially exposing sensitive information or vulnerabilities to attackers. Debuggable applications may leak information or have security weaknesses that could be exploited.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>The android:debuggable attribute is set to "false" in release builds to prevent exposing sensitive information or vulnerabilities. Debugging features should be disabled in production builds.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify that the android:debuggable attribute is set to "false" in release builds of the application to prevent exposing sensitive information or vulnerabilities. Ensure that debugging features are disabled in production builds. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Unsafe Intent Filters</name>
            <regex>android.intent.action.VIEW</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/unsafe_intent_filters.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>0</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>file</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects unsafe intent filters.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Intent filters with actions like "android.intent.action.VIEW" can potentially expose the application to security risks if not properly configured. Malicious applications or links can exploit these intent filters to launch activities in the application or manipulate data.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Carefully configure intent filters to only allow expected data and actions. Validate input and sanitize data to prevent unintended behavior or exploitation.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify that intent filters are properly configured to restrict access and prevent unintended behavior. Ensure that input validation and data sanitization are implemented to mitigate potential security risks. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Unsafe Broadcast Receivers</name>
            <regex>android.intent.action.BOOT_COMPLETED</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/unsafe_broadcast_receivers.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>0</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>file</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects unsafe broadcast receivers.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Broadcast receivers listening for sensitive actions like "android.intent.action.BOOT_COMPLETED" can be exploited by malicious applications to execute arbitrary code or perform unauthorized actions when certain system events occur. This can lead to security risks such as privilege escalation or denial of service.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Carefully review broadcast receivers and ensure that they handle sensitive actions securely. Implement appropriate permission checks and validation to prevent unauthorized access or execution of malicious code.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify that broadcast receivers handling sensitive actions are securely implemented to prevent unauthorized access or execution of malicious code. Ensure that appropriate permission checks and validation are in place to mitigate potential security risks. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Insecure Network Traffic</name>
            <regex>android:usesCleartextTraffic\s*=\s*"(true|TRUE)"</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/cleartext_traffic.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>1</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>0</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>file</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects the use of cleartext traffic in the application's manifest.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Allowing cleartext traffic (`usesCleartextTraffic="true"`) makes the application vulnerable to network eavesdropping and man-in-the-middle attacks.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Set android:usesCleartextTraffic to "false" to enforce secure communication using HTTPS. Configure a Network Security Config for exceptions.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify the android:usesCleartextTraffic attribute in the AndroidManifest.xml and confirm that it is set to "false" or exceptions are appropriately defined in the Network Security Config. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Proguard/R8 - Code Obfuscation">
        <rule>
            <name>Missing Obfuscation for Sensitive Classes</name>
            <regex>(?i)-keepclassmembers\s+class\s+[^\n{]*(?:password|secret|token|apikey)[^\n{]*</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/missing_obfuscation_for_sensitive_classes.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <exclude>(?i)^\s*(#|//|/\*|\*)</exclude>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>1</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>0</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects missing obfuscation for sensitive classes or methods.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Lack of obfuscation for sensitive classes makes it easier for attackers to reverse engineer the application and extract sensitive information.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Sensitive classes and methods are obfuscated in the Proguard/R8 configuration to prevent reverse engineering.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify that the Proguard/R8 rules include obfuscation for sensitive classes and methods. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Gradle Configuration - Build Security">
        <rule>
            <name>Debuggable Build Enabled</name>
            <regex>debuggable\s*=\s*true</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/debuggable_build_enabled.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>0</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>file</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects if a build configuration enables debugging for release builds.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Enabling debuggable builds for release may expose sensitive data and debugging information to attackers.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Debugging is disabled for production builds by setting debuggable=false in the release build configuration.</developer>
            <reviewer>Check the Gradle build configurations to confirm that debuggable is not enabled for release builds. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Outdated Dependencies</name>
            <regex>implementation\s+['"][\w\.-]+:\w+:\d+\.\d+\.\d+['"]</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/outdated_dependencies.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>1</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>0</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>file</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects dependency declarations with version numbers in the Gradle file.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Using outdated dependencies can introduce known vulnerabilities into the application.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Regularly update dependencies to the latest stable versions to mitigate security risks. Review changelogs and security advisories before updating.</developer>
            <reviewer>Check the Gradle file for dependency declarations and verify that the specified versions are up-to-date. Cross-reference with known vulnerabilities databases (e.g., CVE databases). This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Layout XML - UI and Accessibility Issues">
        <rule>
            <name>Missing Content Descriptions</name>
            <regex>android:contentDescription\s*=\s*["']["']</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/missing_content_descriptions.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>1</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>0</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>file</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects UI elements with missing or empty content descriptions.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Missing content descriptions make the app inaccessible to users relying on assistive technologies like screen readers.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Provide meaningful content descriptions for all UI elements, especially images and buttons, to improve accessibility.</developer>
            <reviewer>Check that all interactive or visual elements in layout XML files have appropriate content descriptions. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Insecure WebView Configuration</name>
            <regex>WebView.*setJavaScriptEnabled\(true\)</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/insecure_webview_configuration.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>magenta</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects insecure WebView configurations that enable JavaScript.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Enabling JavaScript in WebView without additional security measures can expose the application to XSS attacks.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Restrict JavaScript usage in WebView and enable additional safeguards, such as strict URL validation.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify WebView configurations in layout XML files and associated Java/Kotlin files for secure settings. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Insecure Code Patterns">
        <rule>
            <name>SQLite Raw Query with Potential Injection</name>
            <regex>\.rawQuery\s*\(|\.execSQL\s*\(</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/sqlite_raw_query_with_potential_injection.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>3</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>0</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects direct SQLite rawQuery or execSQL calls that may construct queries without parameterisation.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>rawQuery() and execSQL() calls that concatenate user-controlled strings into SQL are directly injectable. Unlike Room @Query with :params, these methods offer no automatic parameterisation. An attacker who controls any string component of the query can read, modify, or delete data.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Always pass user input as the selectionArgs array rather than embedding it in the SQL string. Use ? placeholders in the query and supply values via the args parameter.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify that all rawQuery/execSQL calls use ? placeholders with a corresponding selectionArgs array. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Deep Link Without App Link Verification</name>
            <regex>android:scheme\s*=\s*"(?!https?)[^"]+"|&lt;data\s[^&gt;]*android:host\s*=</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/deep_link_without_app_link_verification.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>0</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>file</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects custom URI scheme deep links without Android App Links autoVerify, which allows any app to intercept them.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Custom URI scheme deep links (myapp://) without autoVerify="true" can be hijacked by any installed app that registers the same scheme. An attacker app can intercept sensitive deep link data (OAuth tokens, reset codes, invite links) delivered via these URIs. HTTPS App Links with autoVerify are the safe alternative.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Migrate custom URI schemes to HTTPS App Links with android:autoVerify="true" and a hosted assetlinks.json file. If custom schemes are necessary, validate all incoming data from Intent.getData() before use.</developer>
            <reviewer>Check all deep link intent filters for autoVerify="true". Confirm that sensitive data (tokens, codes) is not delivered via unverified custom schemes. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Framework-Specific Security">
        <rule>
            <name>WebView Universal File Access Enabled</name>
            <regex>setAllowUniversalAccessFromFileURLs\s*\(\s*true\s*\)|setAllowFileAccessFromFileURLs\s*\(\s*true\s*\)</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/webview_universal_file_access_enabled.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>3</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>0</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects WebView settings that enable cross-origin file access, breaking the same-origin policy.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Enabling universal file access in WebView allows JavaScript in file:// pages to read any file accessible to the app, including sensitive data and private storage. This can be leveraged for data theft if attacker-controlled HTML is rendered in the WebView.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Set setAllowUniversalAccessFromFileURLs(false) and setAllowFileAccessFromFileURLs(false). Use content providers or HTTPS to serve local content instead of file:// URLs.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify WebView settings explicitly disable cross-origin and file-URL access. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Insecure PendingIntent: Missing Immutability Flag</name>
            <regex>PendingIntent\.(getBroadcast|getActivity|getService|getForegroundService)\s*\(</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/insecure_pendingintent_missing_immutability_flag.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>3</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>0</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects PendingIntent creation without the FLAG_IMMUTABLE flag, enabling intent injection on Android 12+.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Mutable PendingIntents can be intercepted and modified by other applications. An attacker could replace the base Intent with arbitrary content, leading to privilege escalation or unauthorized access to app components.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use FLAG_IMMUTABLE for PendingIntents that do not need modification. If modification is required, use FLAG_MUTABLE only with explicit Intent fields set.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm all PendingIntent creations specify FLAG_IMMUTABLE where appropriate. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Insecure Random Number Generation</name>
            <regex>\bnew\s+Random\s*\(\s*\)|\bMath\.random\s*\(\s*\)</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/insecure_random_number_generation.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>3</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>0</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects use of non-cryptographic random number generators in security-sensitive contexts.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>java.util.Random and Math.random() are not cryptographically secure and produce predictable values. Using them for tokens, session IDs, or cryptographic keys weakens security.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use java.security.SecureRandom for all security-sensitive random values (tokens, nonces, keys, session IDs).</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify that Random and Math.random() are not used in security-critical code paths. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="JavaScript Bridge Security">
        <rule>
            <name>JavascriptInterface Exposed Without URL Allowlist</name>
            <regex>@JavascriptInterface</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/javascriptinterface_exposed_without_url_allowlist.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>3</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects @JavascriptInterface methods exposed to WebView without corresponding URL origin validation.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Methods annotated with @JavascriptInterface are callable by any page loaded in the WebView. Without origin validation in shouldOverrideUrlLoading or a WebViewClient that enforces an allowed-host list, attacker-controlled content can invoke these native methods, leading to data exfiltration, local file access, or arbitrary command execution on the device.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Pair every @JavascriptInterface exposure with a WebViewClient that restricts navigation to trusted origins. Validate the current WebView URL before executing any bridge method logic that accesses sensitive functionality.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm that all @JavascriptInterface methods are reachable only by trusted content. Check the associated WebViewClient for URL allowlist enforcement. Verify that no user-controllable URL can reach the bridge. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>addJavascriptInterface with File Access Enabled</name>
            <regex>addJavascriptInterface\s*\(</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/addjavascriptinterface_with_file_access_enabled.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>3</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>3</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects the dangerous combination of addJavascriptInterface and file URL access enabled in the same WebView configuration.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Combining addJavascriptInterface with setAllowFileAccessFromFileURLs(true) or setAllowUniversalAccessFromFileURLs(true) creates a critical local file theft vector. An attacker who can load a malicious HTML file (via a path traversal, zip slip, or download) can call the registered native interface to read any file accessible to the app via file:// URLs and exfiltrate the content.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Disable both setAllowFileAccessFromFileURLs and setAllowUniversalAccessFromFileURLs (set both to false). Serve local content via a content provider or HTTPS rather than file:// URLs. If the JS bridge is required, remove the file URL access flags entirely.</developer>
            <reviewer>Check WebView configuration for the concurrent use of addJavascriptInterface and either file URL access flag. This combination should be treated as high severity and confirmed by tracing how local HTML is loaded. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>WebView shouldOverrideUrlLoading Without URL Validation</name>
            <regex>shouldOverrideUrlLoading\s*\(</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/webview_shouldoverrideurlloading_without_url_validation.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>6</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects shouldOverrideUrlLoading implementations that do not validate the incoming URL host or scheme.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>shouldOverrideUrlLoading intercepts all navigation events in the WebView. Without validating the URL host and scheme, an attacker-loaded page can redirect to attacker-controlled URLs, trigger deep-link scheme handlers, or access internal app functionality without authentication. This enables URL scheme hijacking and open redirect chains originating from WebView.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Inside shouldOverrideUrlLoading, parse the URL and compare the host against an explicit allowlist. Block unknown schemes and redirect to custom scheme handlers only after validating that the URL origin is trusted.</developer>
            <reviewer>Inspect shouldOverrideUrlLoading for explicit host and scheme validation logic. Confirm that unrecognised hosts or schemes cause navigation to be blocked and do not fall through to default handling. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="IPC Attack Surface">
        <rule>
            <name>Implicit Intent Carrying Sensitive Data</name>
            <regex>new\s+Intent\s*\(\s*"[a-z][a-z._]+"\s*\)</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/implicit_intent_carrying_sensitive_data.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>3</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>4</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects implicit intents that place sensitive data in extras without restricting the target package.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Implicit intents are resolved by the Android system and delivered to any application that registers a matching intent filter. Placing tokens, passwords, or credential data in putExtra() on an implicit intent allows a malicious app to register the same action and silently receive the sensitive extras. This is a common vector for credential theft on shared devices.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use explicit intents (setPackage or setComponent) when transmitting sensitive data between components. Never rely on implicit broadcast for delivery of secrets; use bound services or content providers with enforced permissions instead.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm that sensitive Intent extras are only sent via explicit intents with a defined target package or component. Implicit intents carrying authentication data should be treated as high severity. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>ContentProvider Raw Selection Parameter Injection</name>
            <regex>(?i)public\s+(?:Cursor|int|String)\s+\w+\s*\(\s*Uri\b</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/contentprovider_raw_selection_parameter_injection.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>10</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects ContentProvider query/update/delete method signatures that may forward raw caller-supplied selection strings to the database.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>ContentProvider methods receive caller-controlled selection and selectionArgs parameters over IPC. If the selection string is forwarded directly to SQLiteDatabase without validation or parameterisation, any app with read permission on the provider can inject SQL to extract, modify, or delete data beyond their authorised scope. This is a frequently overlooked cross-app SQL injection surface.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Validate selection strings against an allowlist of permitted column names before using them in database calls. Use selectionArgs for all dynamic values and never concatenate caller-controlled strings into query text.</developer>
            <reviewer>Trace the selection parameter from the provider method signature through to the underlying database call. Confirm parameterised queries and column allowlist filtering are applied consistently. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Sticky Broadcast Carrying Sensitive Data</name>
            <regex>sendStickyBroadcast\s*\(|sendStickyOrderedBroadcast\s*\(</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/sticky_broadcast_carrying_sensitive_data.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>3</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>1</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects sticky broadcasts that carry sensitive data in Intent extras.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Sticky broadcasts persist in the Android system after being sent and are delivered to any future receiver that registers for the matching action. Any installed app with the appropriate receive permission can retrieve the last sticky broadcast, including sensitive extras such as session tokens or account data. Sticky broadcasts have been deprecated since API 21 for this reason.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Avoid sticky broadcasts for any sensitive state. Use a bound service, in-process event bus, or LiveData for state that must persist across component lifecycles. Migrate legacy sticky broadcast usage to LocalBroadcastManager or equivalent.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm that sensitive extras are never placed in sticky broadcast intents. Any use of sendStickyBroadcast with credential-related keys should be treated as high severity. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>AIDL Stub Without Caller Identity Validation</name>
            <regex>extends\s+\w+\.Stub\b</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/aidl_stub_without_caller_identity_validation.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>12</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects AIDL Stub implementations that do not validate the calling process identity before handling requests.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>AIDL service interfaces are accessible to any process that can bind to the service. Without checking the caller UID or enforcing a permission, any application on the device (including malicious ones) can invoke privileged AIDL methods and access sensitive functionality or data exposed by the service.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Call Binder.getCallingUid() or Context.enforceCallingPermission() at the start of each AIDL method to verify the caller is authorised before performing any sensitive operation.</developer>
            <reviewer>Inspect all AIDL Stub implementations for caller identity validation. Confirm that either UID-based whitelisting or permission enforcement is applied on every exposed method. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Cryptographic Failures">
        <rule>
            <name>Hardcoded Static Initialization Vector</name>
            <regex>new\s+IvParameterSpec\s*\(|new\s+byte\s*\[\s*(?:8|12|16|24|32)\s*\]\s*\{</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/hardcoded_static_initialization_vector.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>4</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>1</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects use of a hardcoded or static byte array as an AES/cipher initialization vector.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>A static or hardcoded IV destroys the semantic security of CBC and other IV-dependent cipher modes. Two messages encrypted with the same key and IV will produce identical ciphertext for matching leading blocks, enabling block-level pattern analysis and, in some modes, full plaintext recovery without knowledge of the key.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Generate a fresh cryptographically random IV for every encryption operation using SecureRandom. Prepend the IV to the ciphertext so it can be recovered during decryption. Never store or reuse an IV across encryption operations.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm that IvParameterSpec is always constructed from a SecureRandom-generated byte array, not from a static, final, or hardcoded value. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>SecureRandom Seeded with Predictable Timestamp</name>
            <regex>\.setSeed\s*\(</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/securerandom_seeded_with_predictable_timestamp.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>3</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>1</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects SecureRandom seeded with a timestamp or other predictable value, destroying cryptographic randomness.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Seeding SecureRandom with System.currentTimeMillis() or System.nanoTime() makes its output predictable to any attacker who can estimate the seed window. All tokens, IVs, or keys derived from such an instance can be brute-forced within a manageable search space. On Android, calling setSeed() with user-provided values weakens rather than strengthens entropy because the default SecureRandom already uses OS-level entropy automatically.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Do not call setSeed() with timestamp-derived or user-controlled values. Construct SecureRandom() without arguments and rely on the platform entropy pool. For seeding requirements, use SecureRandom.getInstanceStrong().</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify that setSeed() is not called with predictable values on any SecureRandom instance used in security-sensitive generation. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Android KeyStore Key Without User Authentication Binding</name>
            <regex>KeyGenParameterSpec\.Builder\s*\(</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/android_keystore_key_without_user_authentication_binding.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>10</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects Android KeyStore key generation that does not require user authentication before the key is usable.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Without setUserAuthenticationRequired(true), a KeyStore-backed key is accessible immediately after first unlock, with no requirement for biometric or screen-lock confirmation. An attacker with code execution on a temporarily unlocked device (via malware, ADB, or physical access) can use the key to decrypt data or forge signatures without any user interaction.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Call setUserAuthenticationRequired(true) on the KeyGenParameterSpec.Builder. On API 30+, also call setUserAuthenticationParameters() to specify the validity window and allowed authenticator types (biometric or device credential).</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm that KeyGenParameterSpec.Builder chains include setUserAuthenticationRequired(true) for keys that protect sensitive data. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Runtime Protection Bypass">
        <rule>
            <name>Root Detection via Build Tags Only</name>
            <regex>Build\.TAGS\.contains\s*\(\s*"test-keys"\s*\)|"test-keys"\.equals\s*\(\s*Build\.TAGS\s*\)</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/root_detection_via_build_tags_only.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>3</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>3</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects root detection logic that relies solely on Build.TAGS containing "test-keys", which is trivially bypassable.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Checking Build.TAGS for "test-keys" as the sole root indicator is bypassed with a single Frida hook or Xposed module that returns a clean value. A robust root check must combine multiple independent signals: su binary presence in known paths, detection of dangerous installed packages (SuperSU, Magisk), writable /system partition, and system property inspection. A single-source check provides no meaningful protection against a motivated attacker.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Implement multi-layered root detection using at least three independent signals from different layers. Consider a maintained library such as RootBeer as a baseline and supplement with at least one check implemented in native code, which is more resistant to Java-level hook-based bypass.</developer>
            <reviewer>Assess root detection coverage by cataloguing all detection signals. Single-signal checks should be flagged. Verify that detection runs at runtime beyond the initial launch check. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Emulator Detection via Build Properties Only</name>
            <regex>Build\.FINGERPRINT\.contains\s*\(|Build\.MODEL\.contains\s*\(\s*"(?:google_sdk|Emulator|Android SDK)"</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/emulator_detection_via_build_properties_only.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>3</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>4</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects emulator detection logic that relies only on Build string property comparisons, which are trivially spoofable.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Emulator detection based only on Build.FINGERPRINT, Build.MODEL, or Build.MANUFACTURER string matching can be bypassed by modifying emulator properties (build.prop) or by hooking the getters with Frida at runtime. A more robust check combines hardware-level signals (sensor list, camera hardware, IMEI, telephony state) with system property queries that are harder to spoof simultaneously.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Supplement Build string checks with hardware-level signals such as accelerometer availability, IMEI/IMSI presence, and telephony hardware checks. Combine at least three independent signals and consider moving critical checks to the native layer where Java-level hooking is ineffective.</developer>
            <reviewer>Review the completeness of all emulator detection signals used. Single-source Build string comparisons should be considered insufficient. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Data Residue and Lifecycle">
        <rule>
            <name>Sensitive Data Written to Android Logs</name>
            <regex>Log\.[dviweVIWDE]\s*\(.*(?i)(?:password|token|secret|apiKey|credential|authToken|accessToken|bearer|ssn|card)</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/sensitive_data_written_to_android_logs.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>0</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects Android log statements that reference sensitive data outside a debug build guard.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Log.d(), Log.e(), and similar calls are readable by any application holding the READ_LOGS permission on older API levels and by ADB-connected computers. Logging tokens, passwords, or authentication data exposes them to adb logcat, crash reporting SDKs, and analytics libraries that aggregate device logs. This data often persists in log buffers well after the sensitive operation completes.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Gate all log statements that reference sensitive context behind BuildConfig.DEBUG. Remove sensitive field values from production log messages or replace them with type indicators (e.g., "token=[redacted]").</developer>
            <reviewer>Search for Log.* calls referencing sensitive field names and verify that each call is guarded by a BuildConfig.DEBUG conditional. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Sensitive Data Persisted in onSaveInstanceState</name>
            <regex>outState\.put(?:String|Serializable|Parcelable|Bundle)\s*\(</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/sensitive_data_persisted_in_onsaveinstancestate.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>1</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects sensitive data being saved to the Activity instance state bundle in onSaveInstanceState.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Data saved in onSaveInstanceState is persisted to disk by the Android framework and survives process death. On pre-API 29 devices, this data may be accessible through backup mechanisms or residual storage. Sensitive values such as passwords, tokens, and PINs should never be persisted this way as they will outlive the user session.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Do not persist sensitive data in onSaveInstanceState. Re-acquire tokens from secure storage or re-prompt for credentials when the activity is recreated after process death.</developer>
            <reviewer>Review onSaveInstanceState implementations for sensitive key names in bundle put calls. Confirm that no credential or token data is written to the saved state bundle. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Autofill Not Disabled on Sensitive Input Fields</name>
            <regex>android:inputType\s*=\s*["'][^"']*(?:textPassword|textVisiblePassword|numberPassword)</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/android/core/autofill_not_disabled_on_sensitive_input_fields.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_type>lines</context_type>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>3</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <report_format>default</report_format>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_target>match</highlight_target>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects password input fields that do not disable the Android autofill framework.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>The Android autofill framework can cache values entered into password fields and expose them to third-party autofill providers installed by the user. Without android:importantForAutofill="no", sensitive input such as PINs, passwords, and OTPs may be harvested by a malicious autofill service that has been granted accessibility permissions on the device.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Add android:importantForAutofill="no" to all password-type EditText views unless the app explicitly integrates a controlled first-party autofill service for credential management.</developer>
            <reviewer>Check all password and PIN input field declarations for the importantForAutofill="no" attribute. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
</root>