<root>
    <category name="Framework-Specific Issues - Dio (Flutter)">
        <rule>
            <name>Bad Certificate Callback Accepting All Certificates</name>
            <regex>badCertificateCallback\s*:\s*\([^)]*\)\s*(?:=&gt;|{)[^}]*(?:=&gt;|return)\s*true|onBadCertificate\s*:\s*\(_\)\s*(?:=&gt;|{)[^}]*true</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/xplat/flutter/framework/dio/bad_certificate_callback_accepting_all_certificates.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>3</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects Dio HttpClient configurations that accept all TLS certificates via badCertificateCallback returning true.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>A badCertificateCallback that unconditionally returns true disables TLS certificate validation entirely, allowing MITM attackers to intercept all HTTPS traffic from the app.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Remove the badCertificateCallback or implement proper certificate pinning using SecurityContext with trusted certificates. Never return true unconditionally from the callback.</developer>
            <reviewer>Any unconditional true return in badCertificateCallback is a critical finding. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>LogInterceptor with Response Body in Non-Debug Build</name>
            <regex>LogInterceptor\s*\([^)]*responseBody\s*:\s*true|LogInterceptor\s*\([^)]*requestBody\s*:\s*true</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/xplat/flutter/framework/dio/loginterceptor_with_response_body_in_non_debug_build.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects Dio LogInterceptor configured to log request/response bodies without debug mode gating.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Logging full request and response bodies in production captures authentication tokens, session cookies, and sensitive API responses to device logs, accessible on rooted/jailbroken devices.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Gate LogInterceptor with request/response body logging behind kDebugMode checks. In release builds, use no-op logging or omit LogInterceptor entirely.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm LogInterceptor with body logging is restricted to debug builds. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Dio BaseOptions Without Connection Timeout</name>
            <regex>BaseOptions\s*\(|Dio\s*\(\s*BaseOptions\s*\(</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/mobile/xplat/flutter/framework/dio/dio_baseoptions_without_connection_timeout.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>4</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects Dio BaseOptions configured without connection or receive timeouts.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>HTTP clients without timeouts are vulnerable to slow-loris style DoS attacks and can cause app hangs when network connections are degraded or malicious servers delay responses indefinitely.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Set connectTimeout, sendTimeout, and receiveTimeout in BaseOptions using Duration values appropriate to your API's SLAs.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm all Dio instances have timeouts configured. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
</root>