<root>
    <category name="Identity and Access Management">
        <rule>
            <name>Wildcard IAM Policy Action</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[actions\s*=\s*\[\s*"\*"\s*\]|effect\s*=\s*"Allow"[^}]*actions\s*=\s*\["\*"\]]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:actions\s*=\s*\[\s*"\*"\s*\]]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects IAM policies granting all actions via a wildcard (*) permission.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Wildcard IAM actions violate least privilege and may grant unintended access to sensitive operations including data deletion, privilege escalation, and account takeover.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Enumerate only the specific actions required. Use permission boundaries and SCPs to enforce least-privilege guardrails.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm all IAM actions are explicitly enumerated and justified. Wildcard actions are high-severity findings in any non-demo environment. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Wildcard IAM Resource</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[resources\s*=\s*\[\s*"\*"\s*\]]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:resources\s*=\s*\[\s*"\*"\s*\]][IF(MISSING:condition|Condition)]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects IAM policies applying to all resources (*) without restricting conditions.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Wildcard resources combined with broad actions grant permissions to every resource in an account, maximizing blast radius of a compromised principal.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Scope resource ARNs to the minimum required set. Where wildcard resources are unavoidable, apply condition keys to constrain the effective scope.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify resource scope is justified and condition constraints are present. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Network Security">
        <rule>
            <name>Security Group Open to All Traffic (0.0.0.0/0)</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[cidr_blocks\s*=\s*\["0\.0\.0\.0/0"\]|cidr_ipv6\s*=\s*\["::/0"\]]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:cidr_blocks\s*=\s*\["0\.0\.0\.0/0"\]|cidr_ipv6\s*=\s*\["::/0"\]][IF(MISSING:from_port\s*=\s*(?:443|80)\b)]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects security group rules or firewall rules allowing ingress from all IP addresses.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Open ingress from 0.0.0.0/0 exposes services to the entire internet, enabling reconnaissance, brute-force, and exploitation without network-level controls.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Restrict CIDR ranges to known IP ranges (office NATs, VPN egress, load balancer subnets). For public endpoints, use a WAF layer.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm open CIDR rules are intentional and that exposed services have appropriate application-layer controls. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>SSH Port Open to All Internet</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[from_port\s*=\s*22[^\d][^}]*cidr_blocks\s*=\s*\["0\.0\.0\.0/0"\]|cidr_blocks\s*=\s*\["0\.0\.0\.0/0"\][^}]*from_port\s*=\s*22[^\d]]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:from_port\s*=\s*22[^\d][^}]*cidr_blocks\s*=\s*\["0\.0\.0\.0/0"\]]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects security group rules allowing SSH (port 22) ingress from all IP addresses.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Exposing SSH to the public internet invites brute-force attacks and exploitation of SSH vulnerabilities, commonly the first step in unauthorized access chains.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Restrict SSH access to known bastion/jump host IPs or use SSM Session Manager for serverless SSH access without open ports.</developer>
            <reviewer>SSH open to 0.0.0.0/0 is a critical finding. Verify no legitimate use case requires public SSH access. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>RDP Port Open to All Internet</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[from_port\s*=\s*3389[^\d][^}]*cidr_blocks\s*=\s*\["0\.0\.0\.0/0"\]|cidr_blocks\s*=\s*\["0\.0\.0\.0/0"\][^}]*from_port\s*=\s*3389[^\d]]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:from_port\s*=\s*3389[^\d][^}]*cidr_blocks\s*=\s*\["0\.0\.0\.0/0"\]]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects security group rules allowing RDP (port 3389) ingress from all IP addresses.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Public RDP exposure is a leading cause of ransomware incidents and is actively exploited by threat actors for initial access.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Block public RDP access. Use VPN, bastion hosts, or Azure Bastion/SSM for Windows remote management.</developer>
            <reviewer>RDP open to 0.0.0.0/0 is a critical finding. Confirm no public RDP exposure exists in production. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Storage Security">
        <rule>
            <name>S3 Bucket Publicly Accessible</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[acl\s*=\s*"public-read(?:-write)?"|block_public_acls\s*=\s*false|block_public_policy\s*=\s*false|ignore_public_acls\s*=\s*false|restrict_public_buckets\s*=\s*false]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:acl\s*=\s*"public-read(?:-write)?"|block_public_acls\s*=\s*false|block_public_policy\s*=\s*false]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects S3 bucket configurations that allow public access or disable public access block settings.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Publicly accessible S3 buckets are a leading cause of sensitive data breaches. Disabling block public access settings can expose data to unauthorized reading or overwriting.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Enable all four S3 Block Public Access settings at the bucket and account level. Use pre-signed URLs for controlled public content delivery.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm public S3 access is intentional and that bucket contents are appropriate for public exposure. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Storage Encryption Disabled or Not Configured</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[resource\s+"aws_s3_bucket"\s*"[^"]+"\s*\{]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:resource\s+"aws_s3_bucket"\s*"[^"]+"\s*\{][IF(MISSING:server_side_encryption_configuration|aws_s3_bucket_server_side_encryption_configuration)]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects S3 buckets or storage resources without server-side encryption configured.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Unencrypted storage leaves data at risk from unauthorized access, storage-layer breaches, and regulatory non-compliance.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Enable SSE-KMS or SSE-S3 for all buckets using aws_s3_bucket_server_side_encryption_configuration. Prefer customer-managed KMS keys (SSE-KMS) for audit trail and key rotation control.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm all storage resources have encryption configured. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Logging and Monitoring">
        <rule>
            <name>CloudTrail Logging Disabled</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[resource\s+"aws_cloudtrail"[^}]*enable_logging\s*=\s*false]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:resource\s+"aws_cloudtrail"[^}]*enable_logging\s*=\s*false]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects CloudTrail configurations with logging explicitly disabled.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Disabling CloudTrail eliminates the audit trail for API calls, making it impossible to detect unauthorized access, privilege escalation, or data exfiltration.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Enable CloudTrail with multi-region coverage, S3 log delivery, and CloudWatch Logs integration. Enable log file validation to detect tampering.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm CloudTrail is enabled and covers all regions and management events. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>VPC Flow Logs Disabled</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[resource\s+"aws_vpc"[^}]*\}(?![^}]*aws_flow_log)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:resource\s+"aws_vpc"\b][IF(MISSING:aws_flow_log|enable_flow_logs|flow_log)]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects VPC resources without associated VPC Flow Logs configuration.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Without VPC Flow Logs, network traffic to and from resources is unmonitored, limiting incident detection and forensic investigation capabilities.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Associate aws_flow_log resources with all VPCs, targeting CloudWatch Logs or S3 for aggregation and analysis.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm VPC flow logging is enabled and logs are being captured. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Secrets Management">
        <rule>
            <name>Hardcoded Secret or Password in Terraform Variables</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(?i)(?:password|secret|api_key|apikey|token|private_key)\s*=\s*"[A-Za-z0-9@#$%^&*!_\-]{8,}"]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(?i)(?:password|secret|api_key|apikey|token|private_key)\s*=\s*"[A-Za-z0-9@#$%^&*!_\-]{8,}"][IF(MISSING:var\.|data\.|local\.|sensitive)]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects hardcoded credentials or secrets directly assigned as Terraform resource attribute values.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Hardcoded secrets in Terraform configurations are committed to version control, visible in state files, and exposed in plan outputs, creating multiple vectors for credential leakage.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use var references with sensitive = true, data sources (aws_secretsmanager_secret_version), or Vault provider lookups. Mark secret variables sensitive to suppress plan output.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm all credential values reference variables or data sources, not literal strings. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
</root>
