<root>
    <category name="Framework-Specific Issues - React Native">
        <rule>
            <name>Insecure AsyncStorage for Sensitive Data</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[\bAsyncStorage\.(?:setItem|multiSet)\s*\(]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:\bAsyncStorage\.(?:setItem|multiSet)\s*\(]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects storage of values using AsyncStorage, which is unsuitable for secrets.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>AsyncStorage is not intended for sensitive secrets and may expose tokens or credentials on compromised devices.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Store secrets in platform-backed secure storage (Keychain/Keystore wrappers).</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify sensitive values are not persisted in AsyncStorage.</reviewer>
        </rule>

        <rule>
            <name>WebView JavaScript Enabled</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[<WebView[^>]*javaScriptEnabled\s*=\s*\{?true\}?]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:<WebView[^>]*javaScriptEnabled\s*=\s*\{?true\}?]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects JavaScript-enabled React Native WebView usage.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Improper WebView restrictions can allow script injection, malicious redirects, or data exfiltration.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Restrict navigation targets and disable JavaScript unless required.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm WebView origin allowlist and navigation blocking logic are enforced.</reviewer>
        </rule>

        <rule>
            <name>Arbitrary External URL Opening</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[\bLinking\.openURL\s*\(]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:\bLinking\.openURL\s*\(]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects external URL launches that require strict allowlist validation.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Opening attacker-controlled URLs can trigger phishing, malicious apps, or sensitive action abuse.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Validate URI schemes and host allowlists before opening external URLs.</developer>
            <reviewer>Review URL construction paths and enforce allowlists.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>

    <category name="Platform-Specific Issues - Android">
        <rule>
            <name>Android Cleartext Traffic Enabled</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[usesCleartextTraffic\s*=\s*"?(?:true|TRUE)"?]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:usesCleartextTraffic\s*=\s*"?(?:true|TRUE)"?]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects cleartext traffic allowance in Android-side configuration files.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Allowing cleartext traffic weakens confidentiality and enables man-in-the-middle interception.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Disable cleartext traffic and enforce HTTPS endpoints.</developer>
            <reviewer>Check Android networking policy for cleartext exceptions.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>

    <category name="Platform-Specific Issues - iOS">
        <rule>
            <name>ATS Arbitrary Loads Enabled</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[NSAllowsArbitraryLoads\s*</key>\s*<true\s*/>]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:NSAllowsArbitraryLoads\s*</key>\s*<true\s*/>]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects iOS transport policy relaxation in React Native iOS projects.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Relaxed ATS controls can permit insecure HTTP traffic and increase interception risk.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use ATS defaults and limit exceptions to specific trusted domains.</developer>
            <reviewer>Validate ATS exceptions and domain scoping in iOS plist files.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
</root>
