<root>
    <category name="Framework-Specific Issues - Xamarin/.NET Mobile">
        <rule>
            <name>Insecure Local Storage of Secrets</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[\b(?:Preferences\.Set|Application\.Current\.Properties\[|SecureStorage\.SetAsync\s*\()]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:\b(?:Preferences\.Set|Application\.Current\.Properties\[|SecureStorage\.SetAsync\s*\()]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects local persistence patterns where sensitive value handling should be verified.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Improper secret storage can expose credentials or tokens to local compromise.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use secure storage APIs for secrets and avoid plaintext persistence in app preferences.</developer>
            <reviewer>Inspect storage calls to ensure only non-sensitive values use preference stores.</reviewer>
        </rule>

        <rule>
            <name>TLS Certificate Validation Bypass Callback</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[ServerCertificateCustomValidationCallback\s*=\s*\(.*\)\s*=>\s*true]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:ServerCertificateCustomValidationCallback\s*=\s*\(.*\)\s*=>\s*true]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects explicit certificate validation bypass in HTTP client configuration.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Bypassing certificate validation enables man-in-the-middle interception.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use default certificate validation or robust pinning with proper fallback handling.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify no certificate callback unconditionally returns true.</reviewer>
        </rule>

        <rule>
            <name>WebView JavaScript Enabled</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[\b(?:WebView|HybridWebView).*?(?:JavaScriptEnabled\s*=\s*true|EnableJavascript\s*=\s*true)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:\b(?:WebView|HybridWebView).*?(?:JavaScriptEnabled\s*=\s*true|EnableJavascript\s*=\s*true)]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects potentially risky web view JavaScript configuration in Xamarin apps.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Untrusted content rendered with active scripting can lead to data exposure and injection-like abuse.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Restrict origins and disable JavaScript unless necessary.</developer>
            <reviewer>Check WebView source restrictions and script execution requirements.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>

    <category name="Platform-Specific Issues - Android">
        <rule>
            <name>Android Backup Enabled</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[android:allowBackup\s*=\s*"?(?:true|TRUE)"?]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:android:allowBackup\s*=\s*"?(?:true|TRUE)"?]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects Android backup configuration that can expose local app data.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Backups may leak sensitive app data if not encrypted or excluded.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Disable backups for sensitive apps or explicitly exclude sensitive data.</developer>
            <reviewer>Validate backup policy based on data sensitivity and compliance requirements.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>

    <category name="Platform-Specific Issues - iOS">
        <rule>
            <name>iOS Keychain Accessibility Too Broad</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[kSecAttrAccessibleAlways]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:kSecAttrAccessibleAlways]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects permissive keychain accessibility constants in iOS-specific Xamarin code.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Weak keychain accessibility can increase exposure of stored secrets.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use stricter keychain accessibility constants aligned with runtime requirements.</developer>
            <reviewer>Review keychain configuration and enforce least-privilege accessibility.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
</root>
