<root>
    <category name="Framework-Specific Issues - Retrofit (Android)">
        <rule>
            <name>OkHttpClient Without Certificate Pinning</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[OkHttpClient\.Builder\s*\(\s*\)|OkHttpClient\s*\(\s*\)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:OkHttpClient\.Builder\s*\(\s*\)|OkHttpClient\s*\(\s*\)][IF(MISSING:certificatePinner|CertificatePinner)]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects OkHttpClient instances created without certificate pinning configuration.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Without certificate pinning, the app trusts any certificate signed by a system-trusted CA. Attackers using corporate proxies, rogue CAs, or user-installed certificates can intercept HTTPS traffic via MITM.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Add a CertificatePinner to the OkHttpClient builder pinning the server's public key hash. Use certificate transparency logs to detect unauthorized certificate issuance.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm OkHttpClient configurations include certificate pinning for all sensitive API endpoints. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>OkHttp Body-Level Logging in Production</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[HttpLoggingInterceptor\s*\(\s*\)[^;)]*level\s*=\s*HttpLoggingInterceptor\.Level\.BODY|setLevel\s*\(\s*HttpLoggingInterceptor\.Level\.BODY\s*\)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:HttpLoggingInterceptor\.Level\.BODY][IF(MISSING:BuildConfig\.DEBUG|if.*debug|if.*DEBUG|FLAVOR)]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects OkHttp logging interceptor configured at BODY level potentially in production builds.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>BODY-level logging captures full request and response bodies including authentication tokens, API keys, and sensitive user data to Logcat, which is accessible to other apps on rooted devices.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Gate BODY-level logging behind BuildConfig.DEBUG checks. Use NONE or BASIC level for release builds.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm BODY-level logging is restricted to debug builds and does not exist in release build paths. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>TrustManager Accepting All Certificates</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[override\s+fun\s+checkServerTrusted|override\s+fun\s+checkClientTrusted|X509TrustManager[^}]*\{\s*\}|getAcceptedIssuers\s*\(\s*\)\s*=\s*(?:null|arrayOf\s*\(\s*\))]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:X509TrustManager[^}]*\{\s*\}|override\s+fun\s+checkServerTrusted][IF(MISSING:CertPathValidator|PKIXParameters|validate|checkValidity)]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects custom TrustManager implementations that perform no certificate validation.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Empty or no-op checkServerTrusted() implementations accept any TLS certificate, completely disabling TLS authentication and enabling trivial MITM attacks against all HTTPS connections from the app.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Remove custom TrustManagers entirely and rely on the Android default trust store. If custom trust is required (e.g., private CA), implement full certificate chain validation using CertPathValidator.</developer>
            <reviewer>Any no-op TrustManager is a critical finding. Confirm removal and verify all TLS connections use default or properly validated trust anchors. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
</root>
