<root>
    <category name="Image and Base Configuration">
        <rule>
            <name>Running as Root User</name>
            <regex>^USER\s+(?:root|0)\s*$</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/dockerfile/core/running_as_root_user.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>1</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>1</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>file</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects Dockerfiles that explicitly set or retain root as the container runtime user.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Running containers as root means any process escape or container breakout yields full host root privileges, dramatically increasing the impact of exploitation.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Add a non-root USER instruction before the final CMD/ENTRYPOINT. Create a dedicated application user with RUN useradd -r -u 1001 appuser and reference it with USER appuser.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm the final USER directive before CMD or ENTRYPOINT is a non-root identity. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>No USER Directive Present</name>
            <regex>^(?:ENTRYPOINT|CMD)\s</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/dockerfile/core/no_user_directive_present.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>1</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>1</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>file</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects Dockerfiles that do not specify a USER directive, defaulting to root at runtime.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Without a USER directive the container process defaults to root, unnecessarily expanding the attack surface.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Add a non-root USER directive before the ENTRYPOINT or CMD instruction.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify an explicit non-root USER is defined before container startup. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Using latest Tag for Base Image</name>
            <regex>^FROM\s+\S+:latest\b|^FROM\s+(?!scratch\b)\S+\s*$</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/dockerfile/core/using_latest_tag_for_base_image.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>1</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>1</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>file</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects use of the latest tag or untagged image references in FROM instructions.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Using latest or no tag causes unpredictable image resolution, can silently introduce vulnerable base image versions, and makes builds non-reproducible.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Pin base images to specific immutable digest hashes (FROM ubuntu@sha256:...) or fixed version tags (FROM ubuntu:22.04).</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm all base image references include pinned version tags or digest hashes. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Secret and Credential Exposure">
        <rule>
            <name>Secret Passed via ENV Instruction</name>
            <regex>(?i)^ENV\s+(?:PASSWORD|SECRET|API_KEY|APIKEY|TOKEN|ACCESS_KEY|PRIVATE_KEY|AUTH_TOKEN)\s*=?\s*\S</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/dockerfile/core/secret_passed_via_env_instruction.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>1</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>0</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>file</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects secrets or credentials embedded as ENV instructions in Dockerfiles.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>ENV values are baked into image layers and visible via docker inspect, image history, and any container spawned from the image, permanently exposing secrets.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use Docker secrets (--secret), BuildKit secret mounts (--mount=type=secret), or runtime environment injection via orchestrators (Kubernetes Secrets, ECS task definitions). Never embed secrets in ENV.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm no sensitive values are present in ENV instructions. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Secret Passed via ARG Instruction</name>
            <regex>(?i)^ARG\s+(?:PASSWORD|SECRET|API_KEY|APIKEY|TOKEN|ACCESS_KEY|PRIVATE_KEY|AUTH_TOKEN)</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/dockerfile/core/secret_passed_via_arg_instruction.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>1</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>0</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>file</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects build-time ARG instructions used to pass secrets during image construction.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>ARG values are captured in build cache and visible in docker history, leaking secrets to anyone with registry pull access or host access to the build cache.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use BuildKit --mount=type=secret for sensitive build-time values instead of ARG. If ARG is unavoidable, ensure the value is never echoed or baked into a layer.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify that secrets are not passed as build ARG values that persist in image metadata. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Private Key or Certificate Copied into Image</name>
            <regex>^(?:COPY|ADD)\s+[^\n]*(?:\.pem|\.key|\.p12|\.pfx|\.jks|id_rsa|id_dsa|id_ecdsa|\.ppk)\b</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/dockerfile/core/private_key_or_certificate_copied_into_image.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>1</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>0</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>file</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects COPY or ADD instructions that embed private keys or certificate files into the image.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Private keys embedded in image layers are accessible to any user who can pull or run the image, leading to credential compromise and impersonation.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Mount private keys at runtime using Docker secrets or Kubernetes Secrets. Never bake cryptographic material into image layers.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm no private keys or sensitive certificates are included in COPY or ADD instructions. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Build and Layer Security">
        <rule>
            <name>ADD Used to Fetch Remote Content</name>
            <regex>^ADD\s+https?://</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/dockerfile/core/add_used_to_fetch_remote_content.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects ADD instructions fetching content from remote URLs without integrity verification.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>ADD with remote URLs fetches content at build time without hash verification, making builds vulnerable to supply chain attacks via URL content substitution.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use RUN curl with an explicit --output path followed by a hash verification step (sha256sum). Prefer COPY from verified local sources or use BuildKit cache mounts.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm remote content fetched via ADD or curl is verified against a published checksum. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Package Manager Cache Not Cleared</name>
            <regex>^RUN\s+(?:apt-get\s+install|yum\s+install|apk\s+add|dnf\s+install)(?![^\n]*&amp;&amp;[^\n]*(?:rm\s+-rf\s+/var/(?:cache|lib)/apt|yum\s+clean\s+all|apk\s+--no-cache|dnf\s+clean\s+all))</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/dockerfile/core/package_manager_cache_not_cleared.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>1</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>1</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>file</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects package installation without clearing the package manager cache in the same layer.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Leaving package manager caches in image layers increases image size and retains potentially sensitive metadata from the build environment.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Chain cache cleanup in the same RUN instruction: RUN apt-get update &amp;&amp; apt-get install -y pkg &amp;&amp; rm -rf /var/lib/apt/lists/*.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify package install RUN commands clean the cache in the same layer. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>sudo or su Installed in Container</name>
            <regex>(?:apt-get|yum|apk|dnf)\s+install\s+[^\n]*\bsudo\b</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/dockerfile/core/sudo_or_su_installed_in_container.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>1</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>1</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>file</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects installation of sudo or privilege escalation tools inside container images.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Installing sudo in a container enables privilege escalation paths for any exploited process within the container, undermining non-root user controls.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Do not install sudo or su in production container images. Structure the Dockerfile to grant only necessary capabilities via Docker security options.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm privilege escalation tools are not present in the final image. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Network Exposure">
        <rule>
            <name>Broad Port Range Exposed</name>
            <regex>^EXPOSE\s+\d+-\d{4,}|^EXPOSE\s+0\.0\.0\.0</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/dockerfile/core/broad_port_range_exposed.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>1</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>1</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>file</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects EXPOSE instructions declaring broad port ranges or binding to all interfaces.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Exposing broad port ranges increases the attack surface and may inadvertently open administrative or debug interfaces to the network.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>EXPOSE only the specific ports required for application functionality. Document each exposed port's purpose.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify exposed ports are minimal and all exposed services are intentional. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
</root>