<root>
    <category name="Untrusted Input and Injection">
        <rule>
            <name>Shell Command Execution with std::process::Command</name>
            <regex>\b(?:std::process::)?Command::new\s*\(</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/rust/core/shell_command_execution_with_std_process_command.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>3</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects command execution entry points in Rust applications.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Passing untrusted input into command arguments can result in command injection or unintended process execution.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use strict allowlists for executable paths and arguments; avoid dynamic command construction from user input.</developer>
            <reviewer>Review command construction and argument handling for untrusted data flow and sanitization. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Potential SQL Query Concatenation</name>
            <regex>\b(?:query|execute|prepare)\s*!?\s*\(\s*["'][^"']*(?:\{\}|\+)</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/rust/core/potential_sql_query_concatenation.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>3</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects likely dynamic SQL string construction in database calls.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Dynamic SQL string assembly can allow injection attacks when user input is not parameterized.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Prefer prepared statements and parameter binding APIs from SQL libraries.</developer>
            <reviewer>Ensure all user-controlled values are bound through parameters, not string concatenation. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Memory and Unsafe Operations">
        <rule>
            <name>Unsafe Block Usage</name>
            <regex>\bunsafe\s*\{</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/rust/core/unsafe_block_usage.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects unsafe blocks in Rust code.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Unsafe blocks bypass Rust's safety guarantees and can introduce memory corruption vulnerabilities.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Minimize unsafe usage and encapsulate it with strict invariants and tests.</developer>
            <reviewer>Validate that unsafe code is justified, bounded, and documented with safety invariants. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>FFI Calls with extern "C"</name>
            <regex>\bextern\s+"C"\b</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/rust/core/ffi_calls_with_extern_c.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects foreign function interface boundaries.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>FFI boundaries can violate memory safety and type guarantees if contracts are not validated.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Validate buffer sizes, pointer lifetimes, and nullability at all FFI boundaries.</developer>
            <reviewer>Check FFI wrappers for robust validation and conversion safety before crossing language boundaries. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Unsafe Memory Reinterpretation or Uninitialized Data</name>
            <regex>\b(?:std::mem::transmute|core::mem::transmute|mem::transmute|mem::uninitialized|MaybeUninit::assume_init)\s*(?:&lt;[^&gt;]+&gt;)?\s*\(</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/rust/core/unsafe_memory_reinterpretation_or_uninitialized_data.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects high-risk memory conversion and uninitialized-memory patterns in Rust.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Incorrect transmute/uninitialized usage can violate type and initialization invariants, causing memory corruption, logic compromise, or undefined behavior.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Avoid transmute/uninitialized patterns where possible. Prefer safe conversion APIs and explicit initialization guarantees.</developer>
            <reviewer>Validate safety invariants (layout, alignment, initialization, lifetimes) and ensure safer alternatives were considered. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Cryptography and Transport Security">
        <rule>
            <name>Weak Randomness Source</name>
            <regex>\brand::random\s*\(\)|\bthread_rng\s*\(\)</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/rust/core/weak_randomness_source.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects generic randomness usage that may be misused in security-sensitive flows.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Using non-cryptographic randomness for tokens or keys can make secrets predictable.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use cryptographically secure RNG APIs (e.g., OsRng) for keys, tokens, and session identifiers.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm randomness sources are appropriate for security context and threat model. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Potential TLS Verification Bypass</name>
            <regex>\b(?:danger_accept_invalid_certs|danger_accept_invalid_hostnames)\s*\(\s*true\s*\)</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/rust/core/potential_tls_verification_bypass.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects disabled TLS certificate or hostname validation.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Disabling TLS verification enables man-in-the-middle attacks and credential interception.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Keep certificate and hostname validation enabled in all non-test environments.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify no production code bypasses TLS verification settings. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Error Handling and Information Disclosure">
        <rule>
            <name>Debug Output of Sensitive Values</name>
            <regex>\b(?:println!|eprintln!|dbg!)\s*\(.*(?:token|secret|password|key)</regex>
            <rdl_ref>logic/rust/core/debug_output_of_sensitive_values.rdl</rdl_ref>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>1</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>1</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>file</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects debug logging likely to include sensitive values.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Logging secrets can leak credentials in logs and telemetry systems.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Redact secrets before logging and disable verbose debug output in production.</developer>
            <reviewer>Inspect logging calls to ensure sensitive values are never emitted. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
</root>