<root>
    <category name="Injection">
        <rule>
            <name>Command Injection via eval</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[eval\s+["']?\$\{?\w]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:eval\s+["']?\$\{?\w][IF(MISSING:printf\s+%q|sanitize|validate|allowlist)]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>3</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects eval statements that interpolate variables, enabling arbitrary command execution.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>eval with user-controlled or environment-derived input can allow arbitrary OS command injection, escalating to full system compromise.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Avoid eval entirely. Use arrays for command construction and validate all inputs against an explicit allowlist.</developer>
            <reviewer>Trace the data source for all eval arguments. Confirm no path allows attacker-controlled input. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Unquoted Variable in Command Context</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(?:exec|system|run|sh\s+-c)\s+[^"'][^;|\n]*\$\w]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(?:exec|system|run|sh\s+-c)\s+[^"'][^;|\n]*\$\w]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>3</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects unquoted variables passed to shell execution contexts.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Unquoted variables in shell commands are subject to word splitting and glob expansion, allowing injection of unintended command arguments or operators.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Always double-quote variables ("$var") to prevent word splitting and unintended shell expansion.</developer>
            <reviewer>Check whether the variable originates from user input, environment, or file. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Backtick Command Substitution with Variable</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[`[^`]*\$\w[^`]*`]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:`[^`]*\$\w[^`]*`][IF(MISSING:sanitize|validate|allowlist)]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>3</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects backtick command substitution containing interpolated variables.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Backtick substitution with unsanitized variables can allow command injection via environment or parameter manipulation.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use $() syntax with properly quoted variables and validate all inputs before substitution.</developer>
            <reviewer>Determine the origin of substituted variables and whether they can be influenced by an attacker. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Sensitive Data Exposure">
        <rule>
            <name>Hardcoded Credential in Shell Script</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(?i)(password|passwd|secret|api_key|apikey|token|access_key)\s*=\s*['"]?[A-Za-z0-9@#$%^&*!_\-]{8,}['"]?]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(?i)(password|passwd|secret|api_key|apikey|token|access_key)\s*=\s*['"]?[A-Za-z0-9@#$%^&*!_\-]{8,}['"]?][IF(MISSING:vault|secret_manager|\$\{.*\})]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>1</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>0</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>file</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects hardcoded credentials or secrets assigned as shell variables.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Plaintext secrets in shell scripts are easily exposed through source control, process listings, and shell history files.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Read secrets from environment variables, vault integrations (HashiCorp Vault, AWS Secrets Manager), or secure credential helpers. Never hardcode secrets.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify all credential assignments reference environment variables or secret stores. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Credentials Passed via Command Line Arguments</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(?i)(?:--password|--secret|--token|--key|--api-key)\s*=?\s*\S]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(?i)(?:--password|--secret|--token|--key|--api-key)\s*=?\s*\S][IF(MISSING:\$\{|\$\()]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>1</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>0</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>file</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>red</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects credentials passed as command line arguments, which are visible in process listings.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Command line arguments are visible in /proc, ps output, and system audit logs, exposing credentials to any user with process visibility.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use environment variables, stdin piping, or credential files with restricted permissions instead of command-line argument secrets.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm credentials are not hardcoded in CLI flags. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="File and Permission Issues">
        <rule>
            <name>Overly Permissive chmod</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[chmod\s+(?:0?777|[augo]+\+[rwx]*w[rwx]*|a\+x)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:chmod\s+(?:0?777|[augo]+\+[rwx]*w[rwx]*|a\+x)]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>1</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>1</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>file</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects chmod commands granting world-writable or globally executable permissions.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>World-writable files and directories allow any local user to modify content, enabling privilege escalation or persistent backdoor placement.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Apply least-privilege permissions. Use 640 or 750 for most files and scripts; restrict world access unless explicitly required.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify the permission level is justified and the affected path cannot be exploited by a lower-privilege user. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Insecure Temporary File Creation</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(?:/tmp/|/var/tmp/)[^"'\s]*\$\w|>\s*/tmp/\w]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(?:/tmp/|/var/tmp/)[^"'\s]*\$\w|>\s*/tmp/\w][IF(MISSING:mktemp)]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects insecure creation of temporary files with predictable or hardcoded names.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Predictable temp file names are vulnerable to TOCTOU race conditions and symlink attacks allowing privilege escalation or data injection.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use mktemp or mkstemp for secure temporary file creation with randomized unpredictable names.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm temporary files are created with mktemp and that the handle is used immediately without re-opening by name. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>World-Readable Sensitive File Write</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[>\s*(?:/etc/|/root/|~/)(?:passwd|shadow|sudoers|ssh|\.ssh|crontab)\b]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:>\s*(?:/etc/|/root/|~/)(?:passwd|shadow|sudoers|ssh|\.ssh|crontab)\b]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>1</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>1</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>file</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects writes to sensitive system files including shadow, sudoers, and SSH configuration.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Unauthorized or unintended modification of privileged system files can enable privilege escalation, backdoor persistence, or authentication bypass.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Avoid direct writes to sensitive system files in automation scripts. Use dedicated tools (visudo, usermod) with proper validation.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm whether writes to these paths are intentional, authorized, and include validation. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Network and Transport">
        <rule>
            <name>curl with TLS Verification Disabled</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[curl\s+(?:[^\n]*\s)?(?:-k|--insecure)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:curl\s+(?:[^\n]*\s)?(?:-k|--insecure)]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects curl invocations that disable TLS certificate verification.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Disabling TLS verification makes connections vulnerable to man-in-the-middle attacks by accepting any certificate, including forged ones.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Remove -k/--insecure flags and ensure the target certificate chain is trusted. Use --cacert to specify a custom CA bundle if needed.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify this flag is not present in production scripts or CI pipelines. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>wget with Certificate Check Disabled</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[wget\s+(?:[^\n]*\s)?(?:--no-check-certificate)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:wget\s+(?:[^\n]*\s)?(?:--no-check-certificate)]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects wget invocations that skip TLS certificate validation.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Skipping certificate validation exposes downloads to interception and substitution via MITM attacks.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Remove --no-check-certificate and ensure the server certificate is valid and trusted.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm this flag is not used in production or deployment scripts. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Script Hardening">
        <rule>
            <name>Missing errexit or pipefail Options</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[^#!\s*/(?:bin/|usr/bin/env\s+)(?:bash|sh)\b]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:^#!\s*/(?:bin/|usr/bin/env\s+)(?:bash|sh)\b][IF(MISSING:set\s+-[euo]*e|set\s+-o\s+errexit)]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>1</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>1</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>file</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects shell scripts that do not enable errexit or pipefail safety options.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Scripts without set -e or set -o pipefail silently continue on command failure, potentially executing subsequent commands in an undefined or insecure state.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Add "set -euo pipefail" at the top of all scripts to fail fast on errors, unset variables, and pipe failures.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify critical scripts have proper error handling enabled. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>sudo Usage Without Privilege Validation</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[\bsudo\s+(?!visudo|passwd\s+-l|-l\b|-v\b)\S]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:\bsudo\s+(?!visudo|passwd\s+-l|-l\b|-v\b)\S][IF(MISSING:if\s+\[|check|validate|authorized)]]]></rdl>
            <scan_config>
                <match_mode>line</match_mode>
                <context_lines_before>2</context_lines_before>
                <context_lines_after>2</context_lines_after>
                <aggregate>none</aggregate>
                <highlight_enabled>true</highlight_enabled>
                <highlight_color>yellow</highlight_color>
            </scan_config>
            <rule_desc>Detects sudo usage in scripts without surrounding authorization validation logic.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Unrestricted sudo in automated scripts can silently escalate privileges and perform administrative actions without validation, increasing blast radius of script compromise.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Limit sudo use to specific commands, define explicit sudoers rules for automation accounts, and add explicit permission checks before privileged operations.</developer>
            <reviewer>Review all sudo invocations for necessity, scope, and surrounding validation logic. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
</root>
