<root>
    <category name="Untrusted Input Handling or Injection Flaws">
        <rule>
            <name>Untrusted Inputs: request.GET</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[request\.GET]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:request\.GET][IF(PRESENT:(execute|raw\(|extra\(|eval\(|subprocess|os\.system|redirect|HttpResponse|mark_safe|safe_filter) && MISSING:(escape|sanitize|validate|cleaned_data|get_validators))]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects the usage of request.GET, which may contain untrusted inputs.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates a potential vulnerability related to using user input from request.GET without proper validation and sanitization. Attackers can manipulate URL parameters to provide malicious or unexpected values, potentially leading to security vulnerabilities such as injection attacks (SQL, OS, or LDAP), cross-site scripting (XSS), or unauthorized access to sensitive information.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Carefully validate and sanitize user input received from request. GET before using it in any sensitive operations. Implement strong input validation, ensuring that only expected and sanitized values are accepted from URL parameters. Additionally, developers should be aware of the risks associated with using user-supplied data and follow secure coding practices, such as parameterized queries, output encoding, and appropriate input filtering techniques, depending on the context in which the input is used.</developer>
            <reviewer>Check for appropriate input handling for request. GET. Assess whether developers have implemented proper input validation and sanitization techniques to prevent security vulnerabilities related to untrusted inputs. Also verify the usage of output encoding and protection against injection attacks to ensure the secure handling of user input received through URL parameters. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Untrusted Inputs: request.POST</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[request\.POST]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:request\.POST][IF(PRESENT:(execute|raw\(|extra\(|eval\(|subprocess|os\.system|redirect|HttpResponse|mark_safe|safe_filter) && MISSING:(escape|sanitize|validate|cleaned_data|get_validators))]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects the usage of request.POST, which may contain untrusted inputs.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates a potential vulnerability related to using user input from request.POST without proper validation and sanitization. Attackers can manipulate form data to provide malicious or unexpected values, potentially leading to security vulnerabilities such as injection attacks (SQL, OS, or LDAP), cross-site scripting (XSS), or unauthorized access to sensitive information.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Carefully validate and sanitize user input received from request. POST before using it in any sensitive operations. Implement strong input validation, ensuring that only expected and sanitized values are accepted from form submissions. Additionally, developers should be aware of the risks associated with using user-supplied data and follow secure coding practices, such as parameterized queries, output encoding, and appropriate input filtering techniques, depending on the context in which the input is used.</developer>
            <reviewer>Check for appropriate input handling for request. POST. Assess whether developers have implemented proper input validation and sanitization techniques to prevent security vulnerabilities related to untrusted inputs. Also verify the usage of output encoding and protection against injection attacks to ensure the secure handling of user input received through form submissions. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Untrusted Inputs: Request Usage with require_GET or require_POST Decorator</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[@require_(GET|POST)[\s\S]*?def\s+(\w+)\(.*?request.*?:]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:@require_(GET|POST)[\s\S]*?def\s+(\w+)\(.*?request.*?:]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects instances where either the require_GET or require_POST decorator is used and the request object is accessed in the view function.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates the potential use of the require_GET or require_POST decorator in conjunction with the request object. This may suggest that the view function expects specific HTTP request methods and should handle them accordingly.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>View functions decorated with require_GET or require_POST handle the respective HTTP request methods correctly and securely. It's essential to validate user input and perform necessary security checks when using the request object.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify that view functions decorated with require_GET or require_POST correctly handle the associated HTTP request methods and that the request object is used securely to prevent vulnerabilities. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Untrusted Inputs: user_input_variable</name>
            <regex>user_input_variable</regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:user_input_variable][IF(PRESENT:(execute|raw\(|extra\(|eval\(|subprocess|os\.system|redirect|HttpResponse) && MISSING:(escape|sanitize|validate|allowlist|whitelist))]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects the usage of user_input_variable, which can introduce untrusted inputs into the code.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates the potential vulnerability of using user input without proper validation and sanitization. Attackers can manipulate input values to provide malicious or unexpected data, potentially leading to security vulnerabilities such as injection attacks (SQL, OS, or LDAP), cross-site scripting (XSS), or remote code execution.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Validate and sanitize user_input_variable before using it in any sensitive operations. Implement strong input validation, ensuring that only expected and sanitized values are accepted. Additionally, developers should be cautious about the potential risks associated with using user-supplied data and follow secure coding practices.</developer>
            <reviewer>Ensure that proper input handling is in place for user_input_variable. Verify that developers have implemented appropriate input validation and sanitization techniques to prevent security vulnerabilities related to untrusted inputs. Also assess the sensitivity of the data handled and confirm that relevant security measures, such as output encoding and protection against injection attacks, are implemented correctly. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Insecure Use of Python input() Function</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[input\(\)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:input\(\)][IF(PRESENT:(eval\(|exec\(|subprocess|os\.system|os\.popen|sql|execute) && MISSING:(strip\(|isdigit\(|isnumeric\(|re\.match|re\.fullmatch))]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects potentially insecure usage of Python's input() function for user input.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates a potential security concern related to the usage of Python's input() function for accepting user input without proper validation and sanitization. Using input() in this way can expose the application to various security risks, including injection vulnerabilities. Developers should implement strong input validation and sanitization when using input() to prevent security vulnerabilities.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Avoid using input() for untrusted user input. Instead, Use input() only for non-sensitive, trusted input sources. For untrusted input, developers should implement robust input validation and sanitization techniques.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify that input() is not used for untrusted user input and that appropriate input validation and sanitization measures are applied when accepting user input in Python code. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Insecure Serialization: pickle and shelve</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(?i)(pickle\.load\(.*\)|pickle\.loads\(.*\)|shelve\.open\(.*\))]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(?i)(pickle\.load\(.*\)|pickle\.loads\(.*\)|shelve\.open\(.*\))][IF(MISSING:(trusted|signed|verify|hmac|safe_serialization))]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects insecure usage of the pickle and shelve modules, which can introduce deserialization vulnerabilities.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates the potential vulnerability of insecure deserialization patterns by looking for calls to `pickle.load()`, `pickle.loads()`, and `shelve.open()` with any arguments. Attackers can exploit insecure deserialization to execute arbitrary code, escalate privileges, or perform other malicious actions.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Avoid using insecure deserialization practices with pickle and shelve modules. It is crucial to validate and sanitize any serialized data before deserialization and to ensure that serialized data comes from a trusted source.</developer>
            <reviewer>Identify instances where insecure deserialization patterns are used with pickle and shelve modules. Verify that proper input validation and sanitization are applied to mitigate the risk of deserialization vulnerabilities. Additionally, reviewers should assess whether serialized data is sourced from trusted origins. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Network Calls: urllib2 and socket</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(?i)(urllib2|socket)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(?i)(urllib2|socket)][IF(PRESENT:(connect|send|recv|urlopen|request) && MISSING:(timeout=|ssl|TLS|verify=True|cert_reqs))]]]></rdl>
            <exclude>(?i).*import\s.*</exclude>
            <rule_desc>Detects the usage of network-related modules urllib2 and socket in Python code.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates a potential security concern related to network operations. The use of urllib2 and socket modules can introduce security risks if not handled securely. Developers should ensure proper input validation and consider security best practices when making network calls using these modules.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Carefully validate and sanitize any user input used in network-related operations. Additionally, Follow security best practices when using urllib2 and socket to mitigate potential security risks associated with network calls.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify that the usage of urllib2 and socket modules is secure and that proper input validation and security best practices are followed when making network calls. Any potential security concerns should be flagged for further review and remediation. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Insecure URL Configuration</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(?i)(url|re_path)\s*\(\s*['"](\^|\^\/)([^'"]+)['"]]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(?i)(url|re_path)\s*\(\s*['"](\^|\^\/)([^'"]+)['"]]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects insecure URL configurations in Django's URL patterns.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates a potential security concern related to insecure URL configurations. Improperly configured URL patterns can lead to security vulnerabilities, such as open redirects or unauthorized access to views. Developers should ensure that URL configurations are properly secured.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Review and secure their URL configurations to prevent security vulnerabilities. Avoid using insecure URL patterns and ensure that sensitive views are properly protected.</developer>
            <reviewer>Check for insecure URL configurations in Django's URL patterns and assess if proper security measures are in place to prevent open redirects or unauthorized access. recommend securing sensitive views and URL patterns. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>YAML Loading: Use safe_load</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[yaml\.load\((?!.*Loader=yaml\.FullLoader)(.*?)\)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:yaml\.load\((?!.*Loader=yaml\.FullLoader)(.*?)\)][IF(MISSING:yaml\.safe_load|Loader=yaml\.SafeLoader)]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects the usage of yaml.load without specifying the Loader as yaml.FullLoader, which may lead to potential security risks.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates a potential security concern related to using yaml.load without specifying yaml.FullLoader as the Loader. This practice can lead to security vulnerabilities if the loaded YAML contains Python code or constructors. Using yaml.safe_load or specifying yaml.FullLoader is recommended to ensure safe loading of YAML data.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use yaml. safe_load or specify yaml. FullLoader when loading YAML data to prevent potential code execution vulnerabilities and ensure the safe construction of Python objects from the YAML data.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify that YAML loading in the codebase uses yaml. safe_load or specifies yaml. FullLoader to ensure the safe handling of YAML data and mitigate potential security risks related to arbitrary code execution or dangerous object construction. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Insecure File Operations">
        <rule>
            <name>Insecure File Operations</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(?i)(os\.remove|os\.unlink|shutil\.rmtree)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(?i)(os\.remove|os\.unlink|shutil\.rmtree)][IF(PRESENT:(request|input\(|argv|user_input|params|query) && MISSING:(abspath|realpath|normpath|startswith\(|allowlist|whitelist))]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects the use of file removal functions in Python that may operate on untrusted file paths, potentially leading to security risks.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates the potential vulnerability of untrusted file operations. Operating on untrusted file paths can lead to arbitrary file deletion and other security issues.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Validate and sanitize file paths and restrict file operations to trusted directories when removing files or directories.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify that file operations in the codebase are performed on trusted file paths and that proper input validation is in place to prevent security risks related to file operations. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Information Disclosure">
        <rule>
            <name>Stack Trace or Error Disclosure</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(?i)(traceback\.format_exc\(\)|traceback\.print_exc\(\)|print\(.*Exception.*\))]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(?i)(traceback\.format_exc\(\)|traceback\.print_exc\(\)|print\(.*Exception.*\))][IF(MISSING:(DEBUG=False|logger\.exception|logging\.exception|production))]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects code that exposes stack traces or sensitive error information in Python applications.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Using `traceback.print_exc()` or printing exceptions directly can expose sensitive details like file paths, method names, and line numbers to attackers.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use structured logging frameworks like Python's `logging` module to capture exceptions securely without exposing them to end-users.</developer>
            <reviewer>Ensure that sensitive stack trace information is not printed or exposed to end-users and verify proper use of logging practices. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Database Queries">
        <rule>
            <name>Insecure SQL Queries: raw and extra</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(?i)^[^#]*\.\s*(raw|extra)\s*\(\s*]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(?i)^[^#]*\.\s*(raw|extra)\s*\(\s*][IF(PRESENT:(request|params|query|format\(|f\"|f'|\+) && MISSING:(params=|placeholders|bindparam))]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects insecure SQL queries using the "raw" and "extra" methods in Python.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates a potential security concern related to insecure SQL queries. The use of "raw" and "extra" methods can lead to SQL injection vulnerabilities if user input is not properly validated or sanitized. Developers should ensure secure handling of SQL queries to prevent such vulnerabilities.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Avoid using "raw" and "extra" methods for SQL queries, especially with unvalidated user input. Instead, Use parameterized queries or other secure methods to prevent SQL injection vulnerabilities.</developer>
            <reviewer>Check for the usage of "raw" and "extra" methods in SQL queries and assess if proper input validation and sanitization are applied to mitigate the risk of SQL injection vulnerabilities. recommend using parameterized queries or secure SQL query-building methods. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>SQL Query: SELECT Statements with WHERE or ORDER BY</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(?i)\bSELECT\s+?\*?\s+?FROM\s+[^\s]+\s+(WHERE|ORDER BY)\b.*]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(?i)\bSELECT\s+?\*?\s+?FROM\s+[^\s]+\s+(WHERE|ORDER BY)\b.*][IF(PRESENT:(request|params|query|format\(|f\"|f'|\+) && MISSING:%s|\?|:\w+|params=|execute\()]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects instances of SELECT statements with WHERE or ORDER BY clauses in SQL queries, which may be vulnerable to SQL injection if user input is not handled securely.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates the use of potentially vulnerable SELECT statements with WHERE or ORDER BY clauses. Improper handling of user input in these clauses can lead to SQL injection, allowing attackers to manipulate query behavior and gain unauthorized access to data.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Validate and implement secure alternatives by using parameterized queries with placeholders or bindings to prevent SQL injection risks.</developer>
            <reviewer>Check for insecure usage of SELECT statements with WHERE or ORDER BY clauses, verifying the use of parameterized queries and input sanitization to prevent SQL injection. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>SQL Query: Unrestricted SELECT *</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[\bSELECT\s+\*\s+FROM\b]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:\bSELECT\s+\*\s+FROM\b][IF(MISSING:LIMIT\s+\d+)]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects "SELECT * FROM" in SQL queries, which can expose unnecessary or sensitive data.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it suggests that the query retrieves more data than necessary, potentially exposing sensitive information and increasing the attack surface.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Validate existing queries and specify only the required columns to prevent unnecessary data exposure.</developer>
            <reviewer>Check for insecure implementation using "SELECT *" and ensure only essential columns are specified to limit data exposure risks. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>SQL Query: Direct DELETE with User Input</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(?i)\bDELETE\s+FROM\s+[^\s]+\s+WHERE\s+.*=.*\$.*]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(?i)\bDELETE\s+FROM\s+[^\s]+\s+WHERE\s+.*=.*\$.*][IF(MISSING:%s|\?|:\w+|params=|execute\()]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects DELETE statements using user input directly without parameterization, increasing SQL injection risks.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates a potentially insecure DELETE query that could be exploited for SQL injection.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Avoid using user input directly in DELETE statements. Use parameterized queries to prevent SQL injection.</developer>
            <reviewer>Check if user input is used in DELETE statements and verify that secure parameterization methods are applied. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>SQL Query: Subqueries with User Input</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(?i)\bSELECT\s+[^\s]+\s+FROM\s+\((SELECT\s+.*\$.*)\)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(?i)\bSELECT\s+[^\s]+\s+FROM\s+\((SELECT\s+.*\$.*)\)][IF(MISSING:%s|\?|:\w+|params=|execute\()]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects nested subqueries with user input, which can lead to SQL injection vulnerabilities if input is not parameterized.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates a nested query that may allow SQL injection if user input is not validated or parameterized securely.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use parameterized queries and validate any user input used within subqueries to prevent injection vulnerabilities.</developer>
            <reviewer>Inspect subqueries that incorporate user input and confirm if parameterization and input validation are enforced. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Command Injection">
        <rule>
            <name>Command Injection: subprocess</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[subprocess\.run\(.*\)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:subprocess\.run\(.*\)][IF(PRESENT:(shell=True|input\(|request|params|query|argv) && MISSING:(shlex\.quote|list2cmdline|allowlist|whitelist))]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects instances of subprocess.run() that can lead to command injection vulnerabilities if used with untrusted input.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates the potential vulnerability of command injection. Attackers can exploit subprocess.run() with unsanitized user input to execute arbitrary shell commands, potentially leading to unauthorized access, data loss, remote code execution, or other malicious activities.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Avoid using subprocess. run() with untrusted user input whenever possible. If their usage is necessary, it is crucial to employ strict input validation, input sanitization, and command parameterization techniques to prevent command injection attacks. Also consider using safer alternatives or language constructs that mitigate command execution risks.</developer>
            <reviewer>Check for the secure usage of subprocess. run() and assess if user input is properly validated, sanitized, and appropriately used as command parameters. Ensure that developers have implemented strong input validation measures, command parameterization techniques, and proper context-aware security controls to mitigate command injection vulnerabilities. Also validate if safe alternatives or language constructs have been considered to minimize the risks associated with shell command execution. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Subprocess Modules: os.system, os.spawn, os.popen, popen2., os.kill, commands.</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(?i)(os\.system|os\.spawn|os\.popen|popen2\.|os\.kill|commands\.)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(?i)(os\.system|os\.spawn|os\.popen|popen2\.|os\.kill|commands\.)][IF(PRESENT:(input\(|request|params|query|argv) && MISSING:(shlex\.quote|allowlist|whitelist))]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects the usage of subprocess-related modules and functions in Python code.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates a potential security concern related to subprocess handling. The use of subprocess-related functions and modules can introduce security risks if not handled securely. Developers should ensure proper input validation, sanitization, and security measures when executing system commands or managing subprocesses.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Carefully validate and sanitize any user input used in subprocess-related operations. Also follow security best practices when using subprocess functions and modules to mitigate potential security risks associated with subprocess handling.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify that the usage of subprocess-related functions and modules is secure and that proper input validation, sanitization, and security best practices are followed when handling subprocesses. Any potential security concerns should be flagged for further review and remediation. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Command Injection: eval()</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(^|\s|=\s?)eval\(]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(^|\s|=\s?)eval\(][IF(PRESENT:(input\(|request|params|query|user_input|base64|pickle) && MISSING:(allowlist|whitelist))]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects instances of eval() that can lead to command injection vulnerabilities if used with untrusted input.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates the potential vulnerability of command injection. Attackers can exploit eval() with unsanitized user input to execute arbitrary code, potentially leading to unauthorized access, data loss, remote code execution, or other malicious activities.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Avoid using eval() with untrusted user input whenever possible. If its usage is necessary, it is crucial to employ strict input validation, input sanitization, and command parameterization techniques to prevent command injection attacks. Also consider using safer alternatives or language constructs that mitigate command execution risks.</developer>
            <reviewer>Check for the secure usage of eval() and assess if user input is properly validated, sanitized, and appropriately used as command parameters. Ensure that developers have implemented strong input validation measures, command parameterization techniques, and proper context-aware security controls to mitigate command injection vulnerabilities. Also validate if safe alternatives or language constructs have been considered to minimize the risks associated with shell command execution. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Arbitrary Code Execution">
        <rule>
            <name>Arbitrary Code Execution: eval()</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[\beval\(.+\)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:\beval\(.+\)][IF(PRESENT:(input\(|request|params|query|user_input|base64|pickle) && MISSING:(allowlist|whitelist))]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects the usage of eval() function, which can lead to arbitrary code execution vulnerabilities.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates the potential vulnerability of code injection. Attackers can exploit the eval() function to execute arbitrary code, potentially gaining unauthorized access, compromising data integrity, or executing malicious actions on the server.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Avoid using eval() function whenever possible. If its usage is unavoidable, it is crucial to validate and sanitize any user-supplied input before passing it to eval(). Developers should explore safer alternatives or restrict the execution to a limited and controlled environment.</developer>
            <reviewer>Identify the presence of eval() function and assess if user input is directly passed to eval(). Verify that proper input validation and sanitization are applied to mitigate the risk of arbitrary code execution vulnerabilities. Additionally, reviewers should encourage the use of safer alternatives and evaluate the execution context to minimize potential harm. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Session and State Management">
        <rule>
            <name>Insecure Session Cookies or CSRF Tokens Configuration</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(?i)\b(SESSION_COOKIE_SECURE|CSRF_COOKIE_SECURE)\s*=\s*False\b]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(?i)\b(SESSION_COOKIE_SECURE|CSRF_COOKIE_SECURE)\s*=\s*False\b]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects potential security vulnerabilities related to insecure session cookies or CSRF token configurations in Django and similar Python web frameworks.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates a potential security vulnerability. Insecure settings for session cookies (SESSION_COOKIE_SECURE=False) or CSRF tokens (CSRF_COOKIE_SECURE=False) can expose the application to security risks, including session hijacking and cross-site request forgery (CSRF) attacks. Developers should ensure that session cookies are set as secure (SESSION_COOKIE_SECURE=True) and that CSRF tokens are correctly configured (CSRF_COOKIE_SECURE=True) to enhance the security of the application.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Review and update the configuration settings for session cookies and CSRF tokens in the application's security settings. Ensure that SESSION_COOKIE_SECURE is set to True to make session cookies secure (HTTPS-only), and set CSRF_COOKIE_SECURE to True to enhance protection against CSRF attacks.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify that the SESSION_COOKIE_SECURE and CSRF_COOKIE_SECURE settings are appropriately configured as True in the application's security settings. Insecure configurations (False) should be flagged as potential security vulnerabilities and should be addressed by developers. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Deprecated Functions">
        <rule>
            <name>Deprecated Python Functions</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(?i)\b(urllib2|commands)\b]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(?i)\b(urllib2|commands)\b]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects the use of deprecated Python functions and modules.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates a potential security concern related to the use of deprecated Python functions or modules. Deprecated functions and modules may have security vulnerabilities or lack support in newer Python versions. Developers should update their code to use recommended alternatives.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Replace deprecated functions and modules with recommended alternatives to ensure code security and compatibility with newer Python versions.</developer>
            <reviewer>Identify and flag the use of deprecated Python functions or modules in the codebase and recommend updating them to modern alternatives. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Insecure Implementation or Permissions">
        <!--    # This rule is extreamly verbose. Use it only if you know how to filter out what you need.
        <rule>
            <name>Decorators Usage and Placement</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[@\w+\s*(\([^)]*\))?\s*(def\s+\w+\s*\()?]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:@\w+\s*(\([^)]*\))?\s*(def\s+\w+\s*\()?]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Identifies decorators used in the code and checks their placement.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates the presence of decorators in the code. Review the usage and placement of decorators to ensure they are correctly applied where needed and not missed where they are required. Additionally, check for decorators that apply exceptions and review them for potential security issues.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use decorators judiciously and ensure they are correctly placed on functions or methods where they are needed. Carefully review decorators that apply exceptions to ensure they do not introduce security vulnerabilities.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify the usage and placement of decorators in the codebase. Ensure that decorators are correctly applied where needed and not omitted where required. Pay special attention to decorators that apply exceptions and assess them for potential security concerns. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule> -->
        <rule>
            <name>HTTP Decorators: Insecure or Commonly Abused Methods</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(@require_http_methods\s*\(\s*\["(?:GET|PUT|DELETE|.*?)"\]\))|(@require_GET)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(@require_http_methods\s*\(\s*\["(?:GET|PUT|DELETE|.*?)"\]\))|(@require_GET)]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects the usage of insecure or commonly abused HTTP decorators.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates either the usage of the @require_http_methods decorator permitting insecure HTTP methods (e.g., GET, PUT, DELETE) or the presence of @require_GET. Review the usage of these decorators to ensure they are applied correctly and consider whether security measures are in place, especially when sensitive information is transmitted via GET requests.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use the @require_http_methods decorator judiciously and only permit insecure HTTP methods when absolutely necessary. Ensure that it is applied to views where it is needed to restrict or specify the allowed HTTP methods, and consider the security implications of permitting insecure methods. When using @require_GET, take care to implement additional security measures if required.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify the correct usage of the @require_http_methods decorator and the presence of @require_GET in the codebase. Ensure that these decorators are applied appropriately to restrict or specify the allowed HTTP methods for views. Pay particular attention to the security implications of permitting insecure methods (GET, PUT, DELETE) and assess whether additional security measures are in place to mitigate risks. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>CSRF Exempt Decorators</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[@(csrf_exempt)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:@(csrf_exempt)]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects decorators that exempt views from CSRF protection.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates the presence of decorators that exempt views from CSRF protection. Review these decorators to ensure they are used judiciously and do not introduce security vulnerabilities.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use CSRF exempt decorators sparingly and ensure they are applied only where necessary. Carefully review the purpose and security implications of each exemption applied by these decorators.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify the usage of CSRF exempt decorators in the codebase. Ensure that these decorators are correctly applied and consider their impact on security. Pay particular attention to exemptions that may introduce security risks. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Software and Library Version Detection">
        <rule>
            <name>Library Version Check</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[@\w+_version]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:@\w+_version]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects the version of the software and various libraries used in the code.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates the presence of version information for a library. Review the library versions to ensure they are current and not outdated or End of Life (EoL).</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Regularly check and update libraries to the latest versions to ensure security and stability. Avoid using outdated or EoL library versions whenever possible.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify the library versions used in the codebase and check if they are up-to-date. Identify and report any outdated or EoL library versions that may pose security or compatibility risks. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <!--
    <category name="Missing Mitigations">
    </category> -->
    <category name="Insecure Mitigations">
        <rule>
            <name>Insecure Mitigation: Django Safe Filter django.utils.safestring</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(?i)\.safestring]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(?i)\.safestring]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects the potentially insecure usage of the Django Safe Filter (django.utils.safestring), which may indicate an insufficient security mitigation approach.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it suggests a potential vulnerability related to the use of the Django Safe Filter. Relying solely on the Safe Filter without additional security measures may leave the application susceptible to Cross-Site Scripting (XSS) attacks if not used correctly. It is recommended to complement the Safe Filter with proper output encoding and validation to ensure robust security mitigation against XSS.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Developers are advised to avoid relying solely on the Django Safe Filter for XSS mitigation. Instead, Use it in conjunction with proper output encoding and validation to prevent XSS vulnerabilities effectively.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify that the Django Safe Filter (django. utils. safestring) is used in a secure manner, with additional security measures such as output encoding and validation applied to prevent XSS vulnerabilities. Ensure that developers have not solely depended on the Safe Filter for security mitigation. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Insecure Use of Django mark_safe</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(?i)\.mark_safe\(\s*["']]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(?i)\.mark_safe\(\s*["']]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects potentially insecure usage of Django's mark_safe function, which can lead to Cross-Site Scripting (XSS) vulnerabilities.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates a potential security concern related to the usage of Django's mark_safe function without proper output encoding. This can expose the application to Cross-Site Scripting (XSS) attacks if not used correctly. It is recommended to use mark_safe in conjunction with proper output encoding and validation to ensure robust security mitigation against XSS.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Avoid using mark_safe in isolation for XSS mitigation. It should be used alongside proper output encoding and validation to prevent XSS vulnerabilities effectively.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify that mark_safe is used securely, with additional security measures such as output encoding and validation applied to prevent XSS vulnerabilities. Ensure that developers have not solely depended on mark_safe for security mitigation. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Insecure Use of Django csrf_exempt Decorator</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(?i)@csrf_exempt]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(?i)@csrf_exempt]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects potentially insecure usage of Django's @csrf_exempt decorator.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates a potential security concern related to the usage of Django's @csrf_exempt decorator without proper justification. This can expose the application to Cross-Site Request Forgery (CSRF) vulnerabilities. It is recommended to use @csrf_exempt sparingly and only when necessary, with a clear understanding of the associated security risks.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Avoid using @csrf_exempt without a strong justification. When used, it should be thoroughly documented, and alternative security mechanisms should be considered to mitigate CSRF vulnerabilities.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify the usage of @csrf_exempt and assess whether it is justified and adequately documented. Ensure that alternative CSRF protection measures are considered where appropriate. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Insecure Use of Django @login_required Decorator</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(?i)@login_required]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(?i)@login_required]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects potentially insecure usage of Django's @login_required decorator.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates a potential security concern related to the usage of Django's @login_required decorator without proper context and additional security measures. This can expose sensitive views to unauthorized access. Developers should ensure that @login_required is used appropriately and that access controls are enforced for sensitive operations.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use @login_required with caution, ensuring that it is applied to views that require authentication and authorization. Sensitive operations should have proper access controls in place.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify the usage of @login_required and assess whether it is applied to views that require authentication. Also confirm the presence of appropriate access controls for sensitive operations. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Using Django's Safe Filter</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(?i)\.safe_filter\s*\(\s*]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(?i)\.safe_filter\s*\(\s*]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects the use of Django's Safe Filter without proper sanitization.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>If this rule matches, it indicates a potential security concern related to the use of Django's Safe Filter without proper sanitization. Using Safe Filter without ensuring that the content is safe can lead to Cross-Site Scripting (XSS) vulnerabilities.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Only use Django's Safe Filter on content that has been properly sanitized and validated to be safe from XSS attacks.</developer>
            <reviewer>Check for the use of Django's Safe Filter and assess if the content passed to it is properly sanitized and validated to prevent XSS vulnerabilities. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Server-Side Request Forgery (SSRF)">
        <rule>
            <name>SSRF: requests Library with User-Controlled URL</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[requests\.(get|post|put|delete|patch|head|request)\s*\(]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:requests\.(get|post|put|delete|patch|head|request)\s*\(][IF(PRESENT:request\.GET|request\.POST|request\.args|request\.form|input\(|argv|\+ && MISSING:allowlist|whitelist|urlparse|ipaddress|is_private|validators\.url)]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects HTTP requests made with user-supplied URL values that may enable SSRF.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Passing attacker-controlled URLs to the requests library can allow the server to be used as a proxy to reach internal services, cloud metadata endpoints, or perform network reconnaissance.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Validate URL scheme and host against an explicit allowlist before making outbound requests. Block access to private IP ranges and cloud metadata addresses (169.254.169.254).</developer>
            <reviewer>Trace URL parameter origin to outbound request sinks and verify that destination validation is present. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>SSRF: urllib with User-Controlled URL</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[urllib\.request\.urlopen\s*\(|urllib\.urlopen\s*\(|httplib|http\.client\.HTTPConnection\s*\(]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:urllib\.request\.urlopen\s*\(|urllib\.urlopen\s*\(][IF(PRESENT:request\.|input\(|argv|\+ && MISSING:allowlist|whitelist|urlparse|is_private)]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects urllib-based outbound requests potentially influenced by user input.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>User-controlled URLs passed to urllib can be used for SSRF attacks targeting internal infrastructure.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Sanitize and validate URLs before use in urllib calls. Enforce scheme restrictions and block private IP ranges.</developer>
            <reviewer>Inspect urllib call sites for user-input paths and verify URL destination controls. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="XML External Entity (XXE)">
        <rule>
            <name>XXE: lxml etree Parser Without Resolve Entities Disabled</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[lxml\.etree\.parse\s*\(|etree\.fromstring\s*\(|etree\.XMLParser\s*\(]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:lxml\.etree\.parse\s*\(|etree\.fromstring\s*\(|etree\.XMLParser\s*\(][IF(MISSING:resolve_entities\s*=\s*False|no_network\s*=\s*True|XMLParser\s*\(.*resolve_entities\s*=\s*False)]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects lxml XML parsing without external entity resolution disabled.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>lxml parsers that resolve external entities by default can be exploited via XXE to leak files or perform SSRF.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Create an XMLParser with resolve_entities=False and no_network=True, then use it for all XML parsing operations.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm all lxml parse/fromstring calls use a hardened XMLParser instance. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>XXE: stdlib xml.etree.ElementTree Vulnerable Parser</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[xml\.etree\.ElementTree\.parse\s*\(|ElementTree\.parse\s*\(|xml\.dom\.minidom\.parse\s*\(|xml\.sax\.parse\s*\(]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:xml\.etree\.ElementTree\.parse\s*\(|ElementTree\.parse\s*\(|xml\.dom\.minidom\.parse\s*\(|xml\.sax\.parse\s*\(][IF(MISSING:defusedxml|no_network|resolve_entities\s*=\s*False)]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects standard library XML parsers known to be vulnerable to XXE when parsing untrusted input.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Python's built-in xml modules (ElementTree, minidom, sax) do not protect against XXE by default. Parsing attacker-controlled XML can lead to file disclosure or SSRF.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Replace stdlib XML parsers with the defusedxml library which disables all dangerous XML features by default.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify that defusedxml is used wherever XML is parsed from untrusted sources. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Server-Side Template Injection (SSTI)">
        <rule>
            <name>SSTI: Jinja2 Template from User Input</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[jinja2\.Template\s*\(|Environment\s*\(.*\)\.from_string\s*\(|render_template_string\s*\(]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:jinja2\.Template\s*\(|Environment\s*\(.*\)\.from_string\s*\(|render_template_string\s*\(][IF(PRESENT:request\.|input\(|argv|query|\+ && MISSING:autoescape\s*=\s*True|sandbox)]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects Jinja2 template creation or rendering from user-supplied strings.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Rendering user-controlled strings as Jinja2 templates allows attackers to execute arbitrary code on the server via template injection (SSTI).</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Never construct Jinja2 templates from user input. Use render_template() with static template files and pass user data as context variables only.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm that template strings are never derived from user-controlled values. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>SSTI: Mako/Chameleon Template Rendering with User Input</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[mako\.template\.Template\s*\(|Template\s*\(\s*text\s*=|chameleon\.PageTemplate\s*\(]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:mako\.template\.Template\s*\(|chameleon\.PageTemplate\s*\(][IF(PRESENT:request\.|input\(|argv|\+ && MISSING:strict_undefined|escape)]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects Mako or Chameleon template construction from potentially user-controlled values.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>SSTI in Mako/Chameleon templates can provide direct Python expression evaluation, leading to remote code execution.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Load templates from files on disk, never from user-supplied strings.</developer>
            <reviewer>Inspect template instantiation paths for user-controlled source strings. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Path Traversal">
        <rule>
            <name>Path Traversal: open() with User-Controlled Path</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[\bopen\s*\(\s*(?:os\.path\.join\s*\(|request\.|input\(|argv)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:\bopen\s*\(][IF(PRESENT:request\.|input\(|argv|os\.path\.join && MISSING:os\.path\.realpath|os\.path\.abspath|startswith|allowlist|whitelist)]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects file open calls that incorporate user-controlled path components.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Unvalidated path components in file open calls allow attackers to traverse directories and access arbitrary files using ../ sequences.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Normalize paths with os.path.realpath() and verify they fall within an allowed base directory before opening.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify path normalization and base-directory containment checks around all user-influenced file open operations. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
</root>
