<root>
    <category name="Framework-Specific Issues - SQLAlchemy">
        <rule>
            <name>Raw SQL via text() with String Concatenation</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[text\s*\(\s*["'][^"']*["']\s*\+|text\s*\(\s*f["']|text\s*\(\s*["'][^"']*%\s*(?:\(|\w)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:text\s*\(\s*["'][^"']*["']\s*\+|text\s*\(\s*f["']|text\s*\(\s*["'][^"']*%\s*(?:\(|\w)][IF(MISSING:bindparams|bindparam|:(?!:)\w)]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects SQLAlchemy text() calls constructed via string concatenation or f-strings.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Building raw SQL with text() and string formatting bypasses SQLAlchemy's parameterization, reintroducing SQL injection vulnerabilities that the ORM is designed to prevent.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use bindparams() or colon-prefixed named parameters in text() strings: text("SELECT * FROM users WHERE id = :id").bindparams(id=user_id).</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm all text() calls use bound parameters and no user input is concatenated into the SQL string. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>filter() with Raw String Condition</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[\.filter\s*\(\s*["']|\.filter\s*\(\s*f["']|\.filter\s*\(\s*["'][^"']*["']\s*%]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:\.filter\s*\(\s*["']|\.filter\s*\(\s*f["']|\.filter\s*\(\s*["'][^"']*["']\s*%]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects SQLAlchemy filter() calls using raw string conditions instead of ORM column expressions.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Passing raw strings to filter() bypasses ORM parameterization and can introduce SQL injection if the string includes user-controlled data.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use ORM column expressions: session.query(User).filter(User.email == email) instead of filter("email = '%s'" % email).</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify filter() arguments are ORM column expressions, not raw strings with user input. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Hardcoded Database Connection String</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[create_engine\s*\(\s*["'](?:postgresql|mysql|sqlite|mssql|oracle)[^"']*://[^"']*:[^"'@]{6,}@]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:create_engine\s*\(\s*["'](?:postgresql|mysql|sqlite|mssql|oracle)[^"']*://[^"']*:[^"'@]{6,}@][IF(MISSING:os\.environ|getenv|config\.|settings\.)]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects hardcoded database credentials in SQLAlchemy connection strings.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Hardcoded database credentials in source code are exposed via version control, error messages, and process listings, enabling unauthorized database access.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Read connection strings from environment variables or a secrets manager: create_engine(os.environ["DATABASE_URL"]).</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm no connection strings contain literal credentials. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>execute() with String Formatting</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[\.execute\s*\(\s*["'][^"']*["']\s*\+|\.execute\s*\(\s*f["']|\.execute\s*\(\s*["'][^"']*%\s*(?:\(|\w)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:\.execute\s*\(\s*["'][^"']*["']\s*\+|\.execute\s*\(\s*f["']|\.execute\s*\(\s*["'][^"']*%\s*(?:\(|\w)]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects direct execute() calls with dynamically constructed SQL strings.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Using execute() with concatenated or formatted strings bypasses parameterization, directly reintroducing SQL injection risk even within an ORM context.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Always pass a text() object with bound parameters to execute(). Never concatenate user input into SQL strings.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify all execute() calls use parameterized queries. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
</root>
