<root>
    <category name="Platform-Specific Issues - iOS Configuration">
        <rule>
            <name>App Transport Security Allows Arbitrary Loads</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[NSAllowsArbitraryLoads\s*</key>\s*<true\s*/>]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:NSAllowsArbitraryLoads\s*</key>\s*<true\s*/>]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects ATS configuration that allows unrestricted cleartext or weak transport.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Disabling ATS protections can expose traffic to interception and man-in-the-middle attacks.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Keep ATS enabled and define minimal domain exceptions only when strictly required.</developer>
            <reviewer>Review Info. plist ATS entries and validate that all exceptions are justified and limited. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Insecure URL Scheme Registration</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[CFBundleURLSchemes]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:CFBundleURLSchemes]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects custom URL scheme declarations that may require deep-link validation checks.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Improper deep-link validation can allow unauthorized app actions or data exposure.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Validate all deep-link parameters, enforce allowlists, and avoid sensitive actions without auth checks.</developer>
            <reviewer>Assess deep-link handlers for authentication, authorization, and input validation. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Application Queries Schemes Broad Allowlist</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[LSApplicationQueriesSchemes]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:LSApplicationQueriesSchemes]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects URL scheme query allowlists in Info.plist.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Overly broad query scheme allowlists may increase app fingerprinting and data exposure risks.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Restrict queried URL schemes to only those required for business functionality.</developer>
            <reviewer>Ensure scheme allowlist entries are minimal and justified. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Platform-Specific Issues - iOS Runtime Security">
        <rule>
            <name>Keychain Accessibility Too Permissive</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[kSecAttrAccessible\s*:\s*kSecAttrAccessibleAlways]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:kSecAttrAccessible\s*:\s*kSecAttrAccessibleAlways]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects keychain entries with permissive accessibility settings.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Overly permissive keychain accessibility can expose secrets when device security state is weaker.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use stricter keychain accessibility (for example, WhenUnlocked or AfterFirstUnlock variants as required).</developer>
            <reviewer>Check keychain storage options for least-privilege accessibility settings. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>UserDefaults Used for Sensitive Data</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[\b(?:UserDefaults\.standard|NSUserDefaults\s+standardUserDefaults)]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:\b(?:UserDefaults\.standard|NSUserDefaults\s+standardUserDefaults)]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects UserDefaults storage usage which may be inappropriate for secrets.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Storing secrets in UserDefaults can expose credentials or tokens through backups or local extraction.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Store sensitive values in Keychain and apply encryption for high-risk data.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify that tokens, passwords, and keys are not persisted in UserDefaults. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>WebView JavaScript Enabled for Dynamic Content</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[WKPreferences\(\)\.javaScriptEnabled\s*=\s*true|setJavaScriptEnabled\s*:\s*YES]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:WKPreferences\(\)\.javaScriptEnabled\s*=\s*true|setJavaScriptEnabled\s*:\s*YES]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects explicit JavaScript enablement in embedded web views.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Unsafe web view configurations can increase XSS-style abuse and local data access risk.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Disable JavaScript unless required and enforce strict navigation/content policies.</developer>
            <reviewer>Review web view usage for script injection risk and trusted-content restrictions. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Certificate Validation Override</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[didReceive\s+challenge|NSURLSessionAuthChallengeDisposition\.useCredential]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:didReceive\s+challenge|NSURLSessionAuthChallengeDisposition\.useCredential]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects custom TLS challenge handling that may weaken certificate validation.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Improper challenge handling can bypass TLS trust and enable MITM attacks.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use system trust evaluation and pinning patterns where appropriate; avoid unconditional trust.</developer>
            <reviewer>Inspect challenge handlers to confirm strict certificate and host validation logic. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Platform-Specific Issues - iOS Build and Entitlements">
        <rule>
            <name>Debug Logging in Production Code Paths</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[\b(?:NSLog\(|print\(|debugPrint\()]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:\b(?:NSLog\(|print\(|debugPrint\()][IF(MISSING:release|production)]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects debug logging statements that may leak runtime internals or sensitive data.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Verbose logs can disclose user data, API details, and security-relevant internals.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Gate debug logging by build configuration and redact sensitive values.</developer>
            <reviewer>Check logging behavior for production builds and sensitive-data exposure. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Associated Domains Entitlement Present</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[com\.apple\.developer\.associated-domains]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:com\.apple\.developer\.associated-domains]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects associated domains entitlement that requires strict domain ownership and validation.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Misconfigured universal links may enable unintended app routing or phishing workflows.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Configure only trusted domains and validate universal-link handling logic securely.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify entitlement scope and universal-link validation/authorization checks. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Push Notification Entitlement Enabled</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[aps-environment]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:aps-environment]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects push notification entitlement usage.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Push workflows can expose sensitive data if payload validation and notification handling are weak.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Ensure notification payloads avoid secrets and enforce secure action handling on receipt.</developer>
            <reviewer>Review push handlers for sensitive data exposure and authorization checks. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
    <category name="Framework-Specific Security">
        <rule>
            <name>Deprecated UIWebView Usage</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[\bUIWebView\b|UIWebViewDelegate]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:\bUIWebView\b|UIWebViewDelegate][IF(MISSING:WKWebView|WKNavigationDelegate)]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects use of the deprecated UIWebView class which has known security vulnerabilities.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>UIWebView is deprecated since iOS 12 and removed in iOS 15+ apps submitted to the App Store. It lacks modern security controls present in WKWebView, including process isolation, improved content security policy support, and no support for modern TLS configurations.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Replace UIWebView with WKWebView. Migrate delegate methods to WKNavigationDelegate and WKUIDelegate equivalents.</developer>
            <reviewer>Confirm all web view usage has been migrated to WKWebView. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Insecure Random Number Generation</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[\barc4random\s*\(|\barc4random_uniform\s*\(|\brand\s*\(|\bsrand\s*\(|\bdrand48\s*\(]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:\barc4random\s*\(|\barc4random_uniform\s*\(|\brand\s*\(][IF(PRESENT:token|key|secret|nonce|session|otp|password|salt && MISSING:SecRandomCopyBytes|CryptorRandomByte|CCRandomGenerateBytes)]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects use of non-cryptographically secure random functions in security-sensitive contexts.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>arc4random and rand() are not suitable for cryptographic purposes. Using them for tokens, keys, or nonces produces predictable values that attackers can guess or enumerate.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Use SecRandomCopyBytes() or CryptoKit's SymmetricKey/Nonce APIs for all cryptographically sensitive random generation.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify security-critical random values use SecRandomCopyBytes or CryptoKit equivalents. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
        <rule>
            <name>Hardcoded Cryptographic Key or Secret</name>
            <regex><![CDATA[(?i)(apiKey|api_key|secret|privateKey|encryptionKey|password|token)\s*[:=]\s*["'][A-Za-z0-9/+]{16,}["']]]></regex>
            <rdl><![CDATA[[FLAG:(?i)(apiKey|api_key|secret|privateKey|encryptionKey|password|token)\s*[:=]\s*["'][A-Za-z0-9/+]{16,}["']][IF(MISSING:example|sample|dummy|test|placeholder|Keychain)]]]></rdl>
            <rule_desc>Detects likely hardcoded cryptographic keys or credentials in iOS Swift/Objective-C source.</rule_desc>
            <vuln_desc>Hardcoded keys and secrets embedded in app source can be extracted from the compiled binary by attackers using static analysis tools.</vuln_desc>
            <developer>Store secrets in Keychain or retrieve them at runtime from a secure backend. Never embed cryptographic material in source code.</developer>
            <reviewer>Verify no long-lived secrets or keys are embedded as string literals. This can be confirmed as an issue when the matched path is reachable and required controls are missing, weak, or inconsistent.</reviewer>
        </rule>
    </category>
</root>
